<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

<!-- generator="WordPress.com" created="2020-06-28 14:23"-->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>Boundedly Irrational </title>
	<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>Musings on life, economics and everything.</description>
	<pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 14:23:01 +0000</pubDate>
	<language></language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>http://wordpress.com/</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com</wp:base_blog_url>

	<wp:author><wp:author_id>86532646</wp:author_id><wp:author_login><![CDATA[kabirchugh]]></wp:author_login><wp:author_email><![CDATA[kabirchugh2002@gmail.com]]></wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[kabirchugh]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Kabir]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Chugh]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>

	<wp:category><wp:term_id>1</wp:term_id><wp:category_nicename>uncategorized</wp:category_nicename><wp:category_parent></wp:category_parent><wp:cat_name><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></wp:cat_name>
</wp:category>

	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<image>
		<url>http://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Boundedly Irrational </title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
		
	<item>
		<title>About</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/about/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 12:02:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?page_id=1</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This is an example of a page. Unlike posts, which are displayed on your blog’s front page in the order they’re published, pages are better suited for more timeless content that you want to be easily accessible, like your About or Contact information. Click the Edit link to make changes to this page or <a title="Direct link to Add New Page in your Dashboard" href="https://wordpress.com/page">add another page</a>.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>1</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2015-05-08 12:02:30</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2015-05-08 12:02:30</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>about</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>page</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_page_template</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[default]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The ambiguity of morality</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2015/05/08/have-a-cookie/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 12:02:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=1</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[It’s important to have epiphanies. Whenever you’re observing life, dwelling on facts others have written up for you, sometimes a thought of your own strikes you as the ultimate truth on that context. The collectiveness of such epiphanies forms your own thinking, and evolves finally into an ideology.

I encountered such an epiphany yesterday, witnessing the Salman Khan case even when I best tried to ignore it. It’s like such news is force fed to you by the media, so that you engage your time in thinking about such trivialities, drowning your brain in a noise of irrelevance, while the relevant is ignored right in front of your eyes.

But the case provided me with the epiphany, and I should move on to that. It resulted in me in thinking about aspects of human behaviour, which is the most despicably wonderful time pass of mine, for I don’t understand it, but only analyze it.

With the waves of sympathies riding on the actor’s behalf, on misconstrued arguments, made my fear of collective thinking only absolute. Collective thinking dilutes the essence of the complexity of individual thought, which though how much ambiguous in nature ultimately must conform to the majority’s views, which though aims at establishing the supremacy of an altruistic ideology, turns out expectantly and horridly a disaster for humanity.

The question I’ve addressed is primal. It’s a subset of disciplines relating to biology, psychology, sociology, economics and so forth, of which I’ll address these individually.

We memorized in first grade, ‘Man is a social animal.’ The term is an oxymoron. How can an animal tame its animal instincts, and settle down with a society? Well that happened for evolutionary reasons. We evolved from nomads and domesticated ourselves to prevent death from predators, starvation and loneliness, and provide an overall sense of security over thousands of years. But the essence is that the animal instincts are still present in us, today, masked under the veil of civilization.

The Biology then gives way to Psychology. According to Freud, there are two forms of consciousness inherent in man. The animal nature is inscribed by the ‘id’. The id is man’s consciousness which seeks satiation, and would do anything for the attainment of pleasure. That is the basic instinct of man, be it lust, hunger or violence. To prevent such dangers in a civilized setting; we created rules, morals and order, over time internalizing them. This acquired consciousness where humans define right from wrong (in complete subjectivity) is the ‘superego’. This basically differentiates us from animals, as a result of our exceptionally evolved brain. The confluence of these two forms of consciousness forms our actual ‘ego’, with the two in battle sub-consciously. This feeling of discomfort is what psychology terms as ‘cognitive dissonance.’

Here the digression ends, and now I can come straight to the point, with the help of my beloved, Economics. We’ve established by the aforementioned points that man needs society to function and has an individual morally ambiguous nature. Now suppose there are two people. Each would have their own beliefs, and can only function as a society if they conform to certain views, hiding their true thoughts which one might disagree with or even reject. This is classic game theory. The two agents only guess the expected strategy of each and hence act upon that, for maximum benefit. This leads to what we call the equilibrium, which here represents the mutual agreement on collective thought, diluting the overall set of individual beliefs.

This becomes complicated in the real world of multiple agents, where the dilution of thought would increase with agents, and the fear of being rejected on such grounds even more, concentrating and consolidating the accepted set of viewpoints. This is evident in religion, as well as nationalism.

Let me illustrate. The concept of nation states is new in man’s history. Throughout our childhood, we are socially programmed to show absolute devotion to nationalistic symbols like our flag and the National Anthem. This is not bad, until it gives way to jingoism. I recall playing with my friends in a park when there was a sound of our national anthem being played somewhere distant. Immediately everyone stood still. My friends and I didn’t, and we kept on playing. Suddenly we were bombarded with people labelling us to the extent of being ‘Anti-Indian’, just because we didn’t stand for about 20 seconds the anthem was playing. But let me ask this. Do you stand in attention for your own or just because everyone else is standing? The question is rhetoric, as you know the answer yourself.

Human nature is moulded from a central authority our culture has created for us. But there is a solution which is unfortunately double edged. In a large society, there are people who reveal their true nature to other agents they can trust. These people share their true beliefs and reinforce them, creating a distinct ideology. Hence liberal people stand behind the backs of other liberals. But this also means that the majority reinforces the belief of itself only stronger.

Interesting.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>2</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2015-05-08 12:02:30</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2015-05-08 12:02:30</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>have-a-cookie</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_slug</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[hello-world]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>One man’s trash is another man’s treasure.</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2015/09/27/one-mans-trash-is-another-mans-treasure/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2015 14:26:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=5</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[When viewed from one perspective, the title reflects banality of the highest order. On poverty, I can belabour the obvious or I can take this opportunity to address this issue with utmost clarity. I was once beleaguered by the vernacular once I was roaming the state, all coming forth and blasting me with their issues. My answers belied my guilt and I was bereaved of my conscience.

From being a blithe, bucolic adolescent, how come I ended up being a burlesque image of my former self?

All the contrived attempts at being my former self proved to be highly vitriolic. Though it was through my own volition, the thoughts vitiated my brain and I felt disgusted. Some poetically framed them as the vicissitudes of life though such verbose excuses hardly ever placate me.

My reality was now a verisimilitude version of my former life. But I would again be belying my thoughts if I can’t accede that there was an unctuous touch to them.

Such metamorphosis has resulted in a guile version of me.  But it was not my fault I cried over and again. Such hackneyed attempts and self gloating only proved to be histrionic and a gross hyperbole.

I was now juxtaposed with two versions of myself. Overlapping or distinct I didn’t know. Each found the other noxious while I was obsequious to their whims. My ostensible silence belied my fear.

It wasn’t that my thinking was facile but rather had a quixotic flavour to it. But is it too much to ask from people whose sympathies dry out at self wincing facetious cries? I could only dream the universe had more alacrity to proceed and exonerate me through some mystic ablutions. Perhaps too sanguine, if there is such a thing.

Finally I cleared up and avowed my problems and identified the artifices my mind was playing with me. I identified also the apocryphal nature of my thoughts which were supplanted by fear than original thought. I decided it was time to act, and the foremost attempt was abnegation of all forms of self pity. I applied all my mental faculties into the abstruse nature of my problem and with due efforts, my mind acquiesced.

After overcoming the lion’s share of my problem, my mind was still ambivalent and proved to be an antecedent for the oncoming anxiety. When it finally struck, I was prepared and thought of it as an anachronism. I transformed myself from a dilettante and established a resistance, which ended up being the bulwark of my fight against such decadent thinking. Sorry if I bothered you too much. This was an exercise at desultory writing. Hope I enjoyed and learnt as well.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>5</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2015-09-27 14:26:25</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2015-09-27 14:26:25</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>one-mans-trash-is-another-mans-treasure</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[15219876504]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>No sense.</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2015/11/07/no-sense/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2015 18:23:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=8</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[I’ve always been afraid of writing a full open, honest draft about myself. Why is it though? Am I writing for someone else, wanting someone to appreciate my complicated thought structures, appreciate the hilarity that is my life?  What my conscious self tells me is that I am an ordinary individual living an ordinary life, being a cog in the spinning wheel of the world. But it contradicts with my belief of being the most important person I know, and this battle has raged on since being an adult.

It is a rather ominous feeling, when you realize that you’re not invincible. When you see old people in their miserable state while you enjoy the bliss of youth, it passes by fast. The passions of the body wane everyone says. You don’t care. Why would you? But being the prescient being I am, complemented by the knee surgery I underwent and as a result feel shaking joints, that invincibility is all but shattered.

For long I’ve maintained a nihilistic view of existence. People say that I am too idle, since I have no job and spend my time thinking unpleasant thoughts. But do ignoring these thoughts and getting busy is the right approach? I see my grandparents fighting with such philosophies in the sunset years of their life, but at least they have their religion to fall to. Maybe I should be religious? Why deny the comforts of believing in one? I should be selfish. Would ease my stress definitely. Put everything on god. People won’t call me crazy either.

I’ve stopped dreaming. Not dreaming,dreaming, those are out my control and don’t make much sense either. But stopped dreaming of what I should be, what I can be. I do the things I love to do. I am not doing anything that I don’t want to do. Then why am I still unhappy. I don’t understand this aspect of humanity. We always indulge in what we feel like doing. We eat good food, listen to good music. We don’t do anything which would derive us unhappiness, yet we are unfulfilled. We resort to spending money or changing jobs or go on vacations. Being in a happy state of mind and having a long term satisfaction of life are two different things I guess.

On terms of talking about sexuality and relationships, I used to be rather uncomfortable talking openly or even thinking openly about those aspects of my life. It’s my fault though that I lacked certain maturity to be really open about things like fucking and love. Maybe it’s because of the environment I have grown up in. Anyway, at this point of my life, I can say this at least, I want someone. I am a person who is a man child and whose thought process isn’t very stable. That pillar of support I need from someone who is understanding, and instils stability and care for me. Is this a substitute of the role my mother carried out? Is this why I only respond positively to outspoken extrovert women, because I could blindly accept and plead them to take care of me? But I know that this isn’t very selfish, because out of my selfish needs arises a need to provide love also.

Thinking about death scares me. Sometimes the tiniest of changes my body has, like a throbbing headache or a racing heart fills me with health anxiety. I’m unable to continue any work after that. It is so agonizing to see that the potential that lies within me is underused and wholly clouded, that most of the times I question my own beliefs. But there are moments of genius, when I’m reminded that I am under achieving way more than I should be, but my body prefers it that way I guess. Whenever I feel perfect, my body sure finds a way to make everything miserable, so that I return to my abject state of mediocrity and be happy within it.

What do I want to be in this life, what I want to do. I don’t know. I am leading my parents astray. I don’t know what to do. There are many things I can do and should do, but the fact is that I am doing nothing. I don’t know what the future holds, but I’ve certainly tried too hard in these last five years to explain what my mind is doing to itself. There seems to be a trade off at actually understanding myself and being stable or not being depressed, not under achieving but completely unstable. Like letting off the rein of a wild horse, and I’m not willing to take that risk.

I’m an ordinary person, who has suffered things in his mind to perceive that he is different from everyone else. The situations have made me life that. Most of the people think I’m some soft spoken person and judge me as someone who is a man of few words. No I am not. I have too much to say, but those words are drowned in silence.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>8</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2015-11-07 18:23:19</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2015-11-07 18:23:19</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>no-sense</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[16631754361]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The art and/or science of writing an essay</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=11</link>
		<pubDate></pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=11</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Writing an essay is something which scares the heejeebies of the average person. It's an exercise not so much in writing, but in  organizational skills. And for people like me who are impulsive, scatter brained, attention deficited or simply who think as they write, it can be a frightening experience.

The true artists of the game transcend the rules and develop their own style. This requires a lot of creativity, a strong command over the language, and a wee bit of natural language skills. Basically like an art, the good become better at it, while the best write poetry on canvas. However for lesser mortals like us, we can learn the science of essay writing, which is mainstay of this article.

It's clear that even the talented lot of people would struggle in planning their essay which require more than an hour of writing(Around 2500 words) and usually within a pressure or time constrained environment. However with decent analytical tools and a fairly good background reading, there exists a scientific algorithm which can produce not just a decent, but rather an essay which can compete with the prodiguous ones.

If you think the algorithm of an essay is the simple introduction, body, and conclusion where the conclusion is basically a plagiarism of the introduction; Leave now. You're dead to me. The thing is, the science of essay writing as somewhat a more complicated model, where you cannot just expand on a few arguments you have and seek to complete the word limit.

So without further ado, let's begin. <strong>( I advise you to memorize the structure by heart, which will save a lot of time during an examination.</strong>

An essay is an exercise in written debate. You introduce the topic, formulate your hypothesis, break down the topic analytically through your tools, hence give your argument and conclude your findings. Just like an exercise in scientific research.
<ol>
	<li><span style="text-decoration:underline;"><strong>INTRO-FACT-HYPOTHESIS :</strong></span> While many good writers can recall a relevant quote by a relevant personality, it is a very risky endeavour. People usually waste a lot of time in thinking about it</li>
</ol>
&nbsp;

&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>11</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2016-04-28 17:24:14</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>draft</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>This thing called life.</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=35</link>
		<pubDate></pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=35</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>35</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2016-05-31 15:52:46</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>draft</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Economics- The Ultimate Philosophy.</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2016/06/28/economics-the-ultimate-philosophy/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 10:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=36</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Sharing an article I wrote for my college magazine three years back. This article surmises my future research plans as well.

<hr />

<h2></h2>
Life has strange plans for all. It’s a force which can only be controlled so much, making it impossible to plan it out perfectly, and even if it indeed were possible, it would be an extremely tedious and fruitless endeavour. A river runs its own course, you can change the direction of flow every now and then, but ultimately it creates its own path.

Is there anything such as fate? Almost all of us end up doing something we never planned. All humans possess free will.  But isn’t free will just an illusion? This can be explained by economics. We live in a world of constraints. These constraints are not just physical and social but mental as well. Economics 101 taught us that resources are scarce and hence we have to choose. The problem with free will is choice. Choosing is not easy. Combine that with the constraints of resources and abilities and the mess of it all pushes you into unexplored territories. Very simply, we attribute these factors to something mystical, what we call destiny, but it’s ultimately basic economics which explicitly explains it. But is Economics such a perfect tool? Obviously not. It is a dismal science. Human actions are way too complex to comprehend and there can never be enough variables in a model to perfectly replicate a model of consistent human decisions over time. This is what separates Economics from the pure sciences and makes it a Social Science.

I was the epitome of an above average, Indian school student, carrying his family dreams as an illusion of his own. Destined to be the nth engineer, it was a month from entrances I realized that engineering was not for me. I was fortunate that I realized early enough. I learned from my mistake but only partially. I still sought Economics as a stepping stone to the holy grail of White Collar jobs in India, the coveted MBA.

The focus of my article is to say that as from my example, choosing economics and not engineering or MBA was neither free will nor destiny. It was my love for the subject, which attempts to explain human behaviour, and terribly fails at it. How can it, when we fail to explain our own behaviour?

We learn from our mistakes and try again, experienced and improved. Economics replicates this in an unusual way. Like other fields, it learns from its mistakes and gets updated, explaining human behaviour a little better, but simultaneously unravelling  a more complex decision making paradigm we humans have,  making estimation of human behaviour even more random than before.  The fact that such paradoxical forces coexist within a single field is by far more human than in any other subject that I’ve studied.

This is cemented by another example. Central to human philosophy are the notions of existence, reality and perception. We all perceive the world differently, usually in contradiction to the beliefs of other people. A fundamental example of this is the concept of religion. Though every religion shares the same goal, each provides a different pathway, usually in contrast to the pathway suggested by another. Is Economics too different? Different schools of thought within economics provide principles on how to reach the same goal (Economic Development instead of being closer to God in this aspect) usually in complete contrast to the other schools of thought.

Karl Marx bellowed that Religion is the opium of the masses, But isn’t it ironic that after his death he himself would be a prophet of a new religion, communism, which would ultimately shape up more than half a century in the near future?. His theory was based upon contradictions, yet it proves his followers made his teachings contradictory in its self.

In conclusion, I affirm that to understand human decision making, it takes a tool so ridiculous that it fails in every attempt to do as such. A tool riddled with contradictions. A tool, which as it develops makes things more complex than simple. A tool that is basically human in nature. What can be more beautiful than that? A tool which explains everything and nothing and creates even more problems than it solves. Economics is not a religion, it is the ultimate philosophy.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>36</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2016-06-28 10:02:31</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2016-06-28 10:02:31</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>economics-the-ultimate-philosophy</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10208538702397538";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[24266440777]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>How Propaganda Works</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/04/30/how-propaganda-works/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 17:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=45</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[After careful introspection, I have come to the belief that educated folks like us, who have developed tools of skepticism and cynicism and think we are beyond the forces of propaganda today are the biggest and most vulnerable victims of it. This is because we misinterpret how propaganda on us actually works, which takes advantage of our awareness, let me illustrate how we fall prey to propaganda.

Propaganda works by making us believe in nothing.

Propaganda works on some sections of the society by mere rhetoric but works on us by alienating ourselves through the ridiculousness of that rhetoric.

When we see preposterous links, which we arrogantly dismiss as which fool would succumb to this, are deliberately preposterous. It works by making us feel neutral from all sorts of news, maybe cynical or skeptical or entirely apolitical. There can be two examples for this.

A.Memes- Yes, the dangerous power of memes. We see memes which are deliberate trolls, harmless pieces of humor but we miss the psychological impact of them. A meme can bring out a highly sensitive issue and make a joke out of it, from communism to Nazism to even India's shitting problem or simply 'remove kebab' highlighted. This enters our subconscious where we attribute a revolting thought slowly into a humorous analogy, ultimately we miss out on the revolting aspect at all and label such things funny. Things like 9/11 being a conspiracy, even the election of Donald Trump distort the negative heuristic associated with them, and we understate the importance of the issue for a few mere laughs.

B. All news is agenda- When we are consistently barraged with 'fake news' it is overtly explicit such that we lose faith in all news. If the rhetoric from one side says, this news is fake, we view all news with the lens with a skepticism of maybe this attack IS based on an agenda, an ideological agenda. This is NOT good skepticism because we don't have the time and resources to check the validity of all news that we read, that the easiest option becomes to disregard all news together. This fits perfectly with the first side since they now become equals in an ideological battle in the form of select side A or B when one side has made a critical attack while the other has used mere rhetoric. IT IS NOT EQUAL AT ALL!

Taking refuge in the cynicism of all media is the wrong kind of skepticism.

For the ones making preposterous claims, a calculated reply is moot because for them it's a game, for which if no facts are produced, the reply itself is a meme or labels of being a keyboard SJW(social justice warrior).

Not every critique is political in nature. Not every critique has vested interests. Read the stuff before you judge for yourself even if you can't validate them. But perceiving an article to be agenda driven before reading it erodes all value out of it, and just reinforces your bias towards them, or worse, cynicism.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>45</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-04-30 17:25:00</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-04-30 17:25:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>how-propaganda-works</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_skip_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[4556450262]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Is Economics imperial among the social sciences? A philosophical approach.</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/05/02/is-economics-imperial-among-the-social-sciences-a-philosophical-approach/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 06:54:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=50</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This essay was a response exercise in my Ph.D. coursework to Milberg's The 'new social science imperialism'. Not citing, if you have interest you can google it and find the paper. He basically argues that economic imperialism has come in waves with different methodologies as its force, but each force with less conviction to be imperial. This force of imperialism derives its power from Philosophy of Science, of which leading figures are Karl Popper, Thomas Kuhn, Imre Lakatos and Paul Feyerabend. The response which is a basic view and needs to be refined further,(though still contains the point I sternly believe in) is as follows
<div class="page" title="Page 2">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

Demonstratio longe optima est experiential-Sir Francis Bacon (By far, the best proof is, experience)

Economics is the de facto queen of the Social Sciences. Here is to be emphasized the term science, for economics aims to strive towards the epitome of true science, that is the methodology of classical physics. The fact that many models of economic theory have been derived from the physical sciences is no coincidence. Moreover, economists are imputed as having physics-envy, with matching mathematical rigor as a proxy for doing better science.

It is necessary to explore as to why and how this entails economics to have dominance and hegemony among the social sciences. Clearly, physics holds as much hegemony over the hard sciences as the United Nations has control over global peace. So what is it that the author uses the term of Economics imperialism in the social science domain? For that, a careful historical examination of the fields development and the nature of knowledge generated within the field needs to be looked into.

The author traces this history of imperialism into three phases. The first phase comes after the post-war (The second one) development of a new mathematical rigor within economics, with the ascent of what we now dub as neo- classical synthesis and more importantly, models of general equilibrium as developed by Arrow, Debreu and others. The powerful implications of the two fundamental welfare theorems resonated in the entire scientific community, with strong results derived from axioms under certain assumptions, tautologically de- rived with the help of mathematics. This methodology is called the hypothetico- deductive approach, and regarded philosophically as the ideal mode of generating new knowledge as the results derived from within it are certain(unlike probable results of the inductive approach).

In the strict Popperian sense, this made economics the most scientific of all social sciences. However, as any economist would know, this applies to only neo-classical economics, which ascribes to methodological individualism as its foundational framework (a framework developed by none other than Popper). Neo-classical economics also fits into Popper's definition of science, as it adheres to the doctrine of falsification, more than of other competing schools of thought, as well as other social sciences in general.

However, by mid-1970s, it was apparent that the General Equilibrium model didn't serve more than a textbook mathematical puzzle(Blaug,1992) and despite its mathematical elegance, it failed to hold any relevance for the real economy, given the nature of arbitrary assumptions. This divided the economics community into two fields in regard to the future of economic methodology. On one side were the predictionists, propounded by (Friedman,1953) for whom assumptions and descriptions were irrelevant in the face of precise predictions, and the descriptionists on the other, led by Samuelson, who argued for descriptive accuracy and gave the now famous ’F-twist’.

&nbsp;

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="page" title="Page 3">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

This gave way to the next phase of economic methodology, dubbed by the author as the New Economics phase. The methodology of economics gravitated towards inductive and adductive methods rather than the strict hypothetico deductive approach it had earlier followed, relying on ad hoc assumptions and a piecemeal approach to economic problems rather than deriving results from the older generalized theory, resulting in varied sub-fields of economic theory ranging from international trade, industrial organization to environmental economics, addressing uniquely a plethora of questions it had yet not addressed. One of the proponents of this new approach, Gary Becker defined Economics as an approach or an engine of analysis and forayed across disciplines dealing with questions relating to crime, family, marriage and discrimination through economic theory.

The author argues that the hegemony of economics before the New Economics phase could be argued for owing to the superior deductive method com- pared to the remaining social sciences but the new imperialism was based on poorer inductive and adductive methods.1Blaug calls this fall from grace of economics as a science from the pedestal of falsification to the ditch of verificationism.

However, it has repeatedly been asserted by both philosophers and economists, that economists never really practiced falsification, but only romanticized the concept of it. What they instead practiced was Nave or innocuous falsification.(Blaug,1992).The wave of the New Economics approach left an explanatory void both theoretically and empirically and was filled by institutionalism and empiricism respectively. According to the author, the rise of empiricism and institutionalism brought with them a new wave of imperialism, but with even a lesser case for economic hegemony.

The rise of quantitative data analysis and Econometric methods have taken the field by storm in the last two decades. While the development of sophisticated methods of analyzing data has increased the power of generating inferences, but that power comes with a great responsibility and ethics. Under the force of publishing bias, an algorithmic approach of econometric tools to generate papers has eroded the reputation of empirical techniques. There is a well-known adage that under sufficient torture, the data can confess anything. Even when data quality issues are taken care of, the Kletzer Effect that is multiple interpretations from the same data, sometimes reinforcing opposing viewpoints independently.

(The case against inductive methods has been referred as to the ’Black Swan’ problem where justification of all swans are white break down when a black swan is discovered.)

&nbsp;

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="page" title="Page 4">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

In the domain of Popper, both institutionalism and empiricism abide by the mode of verification rather than falsification. The former seeks at pattern behavior while the latter is used to expound established worldviews.

Before getting into the merits or demerits of each approach, a fundamental question needs to be accounted for, which we have taken for granted. That is the age old debate of induction versus deduction. Now it is clear that deduction approach generates truth with certainty, but how do we account for the truth of the premises? Ultimately in this backward induction, the premise has to be derived from induction. The black swan argument against induction is too restricting to do any relevant social science in that manner. It becomes a huge cost to researchers to avoid the black swan when probably there might not be a black swan at all, and that happens more often than not. The author maintains that the new economics theoretical findings are dubious as he gives the example of trade theory and its paradoxes. But he skips over that economists learn from their mistakes and now apply more realistic environments to their modeling from strategic interaction, imperfect information, and completion and so on. Economists have moved on from comparative static based single equilibrium models in linear systems to multiple equilibrium systems with stochastic processes in a dynamic environment. Both have their pros and cons, but it would be naive to base predictions on a theory that maintains the world runs within a single equilibrium point.

The author has misjudged the nature of economic imperialism as related to its methodology. Economic questions hold tremendous importance with actual material implications for entire world population, and economic policy is what rules the world in geo-politics, questions of poverty and standard of living. The basic necessities of life of food, clothing and shelter depends on what economists do in their ivory towers. This power and influence is what gives economists what he dubs as imperialism. Imperialism as defined in the dictionary means a force- ful occupation. Economics hasnt either forced nor occupied the other social sciences. Crossing disciplinary boundaries to better answer economic questions or even attempt to answer the disciplines own pertinent question should be lauded as freedom of research rather than encroachment. Nobel Laureates in Economics boast of the names of Herbert Simon, Daniel Kahnemahn, and Elinor Ostrom among many who used their discipline to answer economic questions by refuting orthodox theories throws light on the rather accommodating nature of the field.

The final point in my response would be in respect of the entire philosophy of the movement of economics in which my central argument corresponds that appraising scientific knowledge in terms of deductivism, verificationism, essen- tialism, reductionism, and other isms does more harm than good. I explain this in the following points: -

• Appraisal of economic methodology appears to share the same fate as economics does in having different schools of thought within the tradition. The Popperian criteria of falsification is just one strand of ap- praisal. Other strands include Kuhns theory of Scientific revolutions, Lakatos paradigm of scientific research programs and Feyerabands an- archistic theory of knowledge generation. Philosophical appraisal fails in this context as Poppers falsification hypotheses are themselves not subject to falsification and hence falls under the paradigm of what he calls pseudo science.

</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="page" title="Page 5">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<ul>
	<li>Following a particular definition of science institutionalizes the generation of knowledge, which is then expropriated by vested interests. Freedom of knowledge generation might be anarchy, but the negative association of the word corresponds to political science and not academic research. If knowledge generation is institutionalized, we wont see accidental and unorthodox discoveries, which includes Newtons classical physics, Galileos experiments, Darwins Origin of Species and Einsteins theory of relativity.</li>
	<li>Its true an anarchist model of knowledge generation would be amorphous and will have a lot of noise to signal ratio where noise denotes bad quality research and signal as quality research. But that holds better than in a system where research is filtered so that there is a lot less noise but drastic cuts in signal too. And the unregulated system of research ultimately does get recognized, in a more democratic space, if it deserves recognition.

This is not to say that economics as a discipline is clearly in the right di- rection and doesnt need any introspection. As I earlier mentioned, the prob- lems within economics plague other social sciences and even the hard sciences. Economists have started questioning their physics-envy as can be seen from vehement criticism of DSGE models by leading economists to development of disciplines such as Cultural Economics and Neuroeconomics which some decades back would have been sheer blasphemy. The imperialism within the field has di- minished, and is integrating with other social sciences as social sciences should, in a normative sense. The future of economics is moving towards Big Data and machine learning and sticking to luddite approaches of sticking with the deduc- tivist model and not adapting to the times is what makes a field truly scieantific. The quote by Paul Feyeraband should sum up as something to ponder on.

"Teachers’ using grades and the fear of failure mould the brains of the young until they have lost every ounce of imagination they might once have possessed." - Paul Feyeraband, Against Method,1965.

References

Blaug, M. (1992). The Methodology of Economics. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="page" title="Page 6">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

Friedman, M. (1953).The Methodology of Positive Economics. In M. Fried- man, Essays in Positive Economics (pp. 3-43). Chicago: University of Chicago Press.

</div>
</div>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>50</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-05-02 06:54:28</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-05-02 06:54:28</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>is-economics-imperial-among-the-social-sciences-a-philosophical-approach</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_skip_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[4608372083]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>A new epoch of Humanity.</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/07/21/a-new-epoch-of-humanity/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 11:34:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=79</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[The past five centuries have transformed us, in a sense, inverted our conception of ourselves and our environment so radically, and in such a short time that to conceive of living in earlier time periods of our history becomes a difficult counterfactual. Whether we call it progress, if we have a notion of what progress should mean, then we have progressed, if not then definitely changed.

Some say that time is circular, or even non existent, but I would conceive of it as spiral, because it’s true that human nature would ensure certain facets of history repeating itself, but history corresponds also to changes in how we see the world, and takes a direction from there.

Most of human history has in some form seen the meaning of life as beyond our means, and attributed things beyond our control to an entity of god. All our virtues, existential discomfort, but even our social and political institutions conformed to a divine entity. From explicit attributions of divine justice by an anthropomorphic being to cosmological justice enshrined in philosophies of karma and dharma, even skeptics found a way to attribute a definition of god, whether it be the sun, our nature, our inner soul, so that this larger set of god encompassed everyone and no one alike.

However, five centuries back, the corruption of humanity in the form of institutional monopoly over god raised questions, and set forward a chain reaction in every sphere of human life, which we now call the renaissance epoch or the enlightenment.

Martin Luther bellowed, that God was democratic, and the clergy had no right over them. People could now interpret the holy cannons as they liked. People started to read and learn to understand the scriptures, and some found the scriptures to lack in proof, or certainty. Descartes, though religious, questioned certainty, and gave us the cogito ergo , the only certainty of our existence because we can be aware of existence.

I wouldn’t go into too much detail for the history is for everyone to read, but skepticism rose like wildfire, and atheism no longer meant roasting at the stake. The pinnacle of this movement of religious questioning reached when Nietzsche roared, ‘God is Dead’, the cosmic divine connection is cut, the lies have been thrown into the garbage of history. But as liberating as liberation from God can be to some, the question soon came, so is there is no divine justice, what do we live for? If there is no God, and I’m going to be a pile of dust, then why not make the most of it? And the seven deadly sins became the seven pure pleasures, until they sowed their own destruction, for values are needed, with and without a god for a sustainable progress of our species.

Nihilism gave way to existentialism, and humans set about starting to explore their own meaning and ethics. Science became a method of finding meaning by ourselves, and soon the Darwins and the Newtons and the Einsteins of the world drafted the sketch for meaning.

But what about ethics?

The evolution of sciences corresponded with the evolution of human thought, and in the wake of secularism, and our increased awareness of our consciousness in response to religious doubts, the rise of the Individual dawned.

I as a person want to be sustainably happy, and have rights, so that in absence of values, may these be my virtues. The Christian ethic was partly forgotten through conception of capitalism, and the need to work.

Political revolutions, Economic revolutions and ultimately social revolutions hinged on the idea of liberalism characterized the epoch, and the ‘I’ became the philosophy of mankind, and nations were conceived of the identity of ‘I’, with my rights, which the new states guaranteed slowly in response to evolution of these institutions.

Fast forward to now.

Despite all differentiated conceptions of sense of reality and morality, as well as competitions from other doctrines, individualism and its forms of egotism, liberalism, libertarianism have solidified and spread throughout the world, which is a fact, whether is good or bad cannot be judged.

However, while the wheels of motions of earlier epochs are still turning, there has been a metamorphosis from within, and a consciousness towards a new epoch is emerging.

Science has outpaced thought, and has created anarchistic modes of organization possible within the internet, connecting everyone in the world, and providing them instant access to all forms of information one needs.

With developments in fields of psychology, linguistics and neurosciences we have again started asking questions, unlike the earlier epoch on the existence of a divine meaning to now questioning our own understanding of meanings we gave to ourselves. We have uncovered grossly humbling biases in our thought and cognition, the limits of our subjectivity and our needs and desires, which transcend to almost being universal. Concepts of the collective consciousness, collective unconsciousness, the genealogy of our languages to a common ancestry, uncovering of the knowledge that our genes reflect varied identities, pierce straight to the heart of the barriers between the I and them we put through our new institutions of nationalism.

Globalization has reached a point of intermingling of people in such a way, that the current tension is nothing but friction of the inevitable, the breaking of the barriers of the I, and recognize the we, across cultures and people. The new epoch is starting from the evolution of human thought in the foundation of a new ethic- Global empathy.

We have always been bogged by selfishness from animal instincts to protect ourselves at any costs, until religious doctrine advised the masses to care for each other. But a commandment is a top down order of ethics. That has been the wrong method of ethics all along, for global empathy comes from within, and truly defines the meaning of a civilization and perhaps re-defines it. Global empathy in the truest meaning of the world global (or universal) will radically change the politics, philosophy, and will help us go beyond ourselves, from thinking animals to beings with the truest conception of our world, and awareness of our connectedness.

Some doctrines have pointed this out since ancient times, but it’s with experience only that such doctrines reveal their wisdom, and the first step to launch ourselves into this new epoch is to go beyond our evolutionary pre programming of selfishness as a virtue. Of course, this can only happen over time, when technology allows us to lax the seeds of competitiveness within us. This includes the dissolving of the nation state, the dissolution of economic scarcity, and resolution of indoctrination of prejudices, which allow ourselves to truly understand a person and perceive no threat from him. When this is achieved, which I speculate is slowly creeping through our awareness, would the problem of ethics resolve itself forever, and virtue will evolve on its own. The anarchistic tool of the Internet I speculate would be supreme in tearing down the hierarchy of ethics we still take from our institutions.

Perhaps this is what Nietzsche meant when he talked about the ubermensch(The ideal man) as the opposite end to the animal which man finds himself to be between in. Perhaps this would be Nirvana and enlightenment which the Buddha attained. All I know is, that the wheels have been set in motion for a new world, and a new humanity.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>79</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-07-21 11:34:05</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-21 11:34:05</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>a-new-epoch-of-humanity</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[7325960187]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10212060215513165";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Of Kierkegaard, Anxiety, and Selfhood</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/07/23/of-kierkegaard-anxiety-and-selfhood/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2017 07:12:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/07/23/of-kierkegaard-anxiety-and-selfhood/</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<strong>Disclaimer</strong>: These are not factually Kierkegaard’s views, but some of his conceptions on which I have built upon and offered not an interpretation, but a reinterpretation of the broad structure of his argument.

&nbsp;

Before the advent of modern medical psychology, the ills of mind were an ailment of the soul for philosophers, but semantics defining the mind and the soul might change, the afflictions do not. Kierkegaard, who is considered to be the father of modern existential philosophy, in his attempt to analyze these afflictions are so contemporary, that anybody who feels existential angst, anxiety, and depression needs to give him a read, which has one of the simplest and lucid analyses of these phenomena.

There are two concepts which form the basis of his analysis. These are the Finite, and the Infinite. Quite simply explained, the infinite represents the realm of absolute freedom of choices and possibilities, while the Finite represents the realm of necessity and actualities of life.

The key to selfhood, which might correspond to the attainment of fulfilment of life represents the balance between these two forces, and any imbalance in the two causes the dread and despair of life.

While losing oneself to the finite is mundane and stifling, and looks forward to the infinite possibilities that life offers, the one lost in the infinite is equally haunting, for the individual then looks towards safety and security of the finite. An analogy is the preference towards living in a gated neighborhood to one living in the wild. Such overwhelming is the infinitude of possibilities in this realm, that one enacts no choice in the possibilities of infinite choice, akin of finding the perfect choice for your life on Tinder. There is always the chance of finding someone better, and hence right swiping ad infinitum.

From my experience, the imbalance between the two is quite simply evident in the transition from college to a career, the infinite offers a desire which is never fulfilled, so we make do with what we get, which rests in the realm of the finite. And once unemployed, the safety of our peers in their own jobs become a source of anxiety, irregardless of them looking for new opportunities in the Infinite.

In more abstract terms, anxiety stems from being in the finite as analogous to standing on the edge of the realms separating these two planes, with the chains of the security of the finite keeping you from jumping to the infinite. This anxiety is what Kierkegaard terms as ‘dread’, or the modern conception of anxiety. The risky attraction. As we age, the responsibilities of life make the chain stronger and tighter, but the temptation of the infinite remains more than ever, so that the dread turns to ‘despair’ , or what we might term depression. The opposite exists in the realm of the infinite as well, where staying too long can make one tempt towards the finite. The desire being that elusive object, makes the individual settle for the necessity or actuality, and in temporary relief the person forgets that the rope towards the finite overtime become chains of his own making, to seek escape from.

The switching between the realms gives one a false notion of the ‘Self’, the realization of one’s meaning in life. The subjective excuses masks one from the objective truth of the suffering in this Sisyphean task, for the objectivity manifests itself only in the infinite relative comparisons between the two realms. Unfortunately, our life is too short for that. Let me illustrate this more clearly. A choice x can only be judged in terms of a choice y. But the true comparison exists in jumping back to x from y, so that we may find truly that x was better all along, rather than in our imagination, but this then means that to truly judge our choices becomes jumping between the two many times (logically infinite times).

In this vicious cycle, Kierkegaard came up with a solution of finding the self ultimately in one’s life, and I believe this solution not only to be rational, but extremely powerful.

<strong>Phase I- The Freedom Phase</strong>

The freedom phase comprises of letting go in the infinite, without adherence to any security or safety. The only way to make choices in the infinite is to make many, and indulge oneself in the aesthetic pleasures of art, love and pleasure. This way one separates himself from the society, through non conformist choices without fear of finite justice. There are two ways to go about the freedom phase, one is the vulgar aestheticism, which satiates too quickly, or a refined controlled aestheticism, which burns like a slow burning coal, until it dies out. The lure of the infinite and search for stability as expected, is inevitable, which leads to the second phase. I define it as a quarter life crisis of the transition stage.

<strong>Phase II – The Ethic Phase</strong>

The individual now in his relief joins the safety of the finite, but the freedom phase allows one to not just choose out of the dread of safety, but the consciousness of the first phase lets him to choose something courageous, so that the bridge between desire and necessity is narrowed. Over time, as the rigidity of the new realm sets in, the virtues and values of one becomes concrete, even if they’re misaligned with one’s true self. The individual reunites with society, in line with his values, and the meaning of life gradually shifts from an aesthetic worldview to one of social duty.

As one makes his bonds within the society, a new dread dawns over him. The signal of the end of a productive life, the ailments which slow one down, and a gradual realization of the certainty of mortality makes one question whether this was all to life, to which the answer comes back, it can’t be. Man is not born to be chained to a role till his death, the minds wants comprehension which the nature itself provides, rather than what he attributes to it. The lure of the infinite strikes back, but one cannot just break his chains and get to the freedom phase now, nobody has the energy nor will. In this impasse, Kierkegaard comes to the third and final state. The transition to this phase I call the mid-life crisis.

<strong>Phase III – The Spirit Phase</strong>

Though Kierkegaard referred to this phase as the Religious phase, the change in our society can present this phase through a parallel where religion can be substituted by the spirit phase, which encompasses religion, soul, mind, whatever one sees something beyond the materialism of life.

The key problem of this phase is to find the infinite in the domain of the finite, and find a synthesis of the two, which can proxy as a balance between the two.

In this stage of life, one cannot just abandon the finite which has now shackled him from all sides. So the individual finds the relief of the infinitude within. While one escapes to introspection to find the objective truth of reality, one cannot just fathom and accept that the reality is just as is, so there is nothing mystical about it. But then how does the infinitude offer itself in introspection?

So one goes through an infinitude of subjectivities on an objective truth, such as the objective certainty of death, on which the infinitude offers itself through either religion, since divine understanding is the desire, because desire as we have now established never fulfills itself. So accepting faith and life after death becomes the ultimate conception of infinity according to Kierkegaard, and finally one finds the infinite in the finite, and the balance is restored, so that dread and despair vanish altogether.

This is an illusion, but if the illusion makes one’s self to be complete, how is it an illusion but something our consciousness was allowed free will for? As Alan Watts recalls a Zen saying- ‘You can give a crying child a yellow leaf which it takes as for gold’.

This phase is characterized not by the need for looking beyond the veil of our immediate reality to a supposedly cosmological reality, which we can never know for fact, so instead we hold on to the desire and expectation (or faith) of such a veil which will someday open up to us, and deep inside we will never want the veil to open until our time is up.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>83</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-07-23 07:12:28</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-07-23 07:12:28</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>of-kierkegaard-anxiety-and-selfhood</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[7390759580]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10212079088664982";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Language, Thoughts, Metaphors and Analogies...</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/09/02/language-thoughts-metaphors-and-analogies/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 14:33:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=85</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<em>The colorless green vapor. </em>

<em>How much does your voice weigh?</em>

The connection between Language and thought has been rigorously studied and speculated. Do we think through language? or language expresses thought? How are our thoughts affected when we don't have any concept of a language? These are some interesting and important questions, but what is obvious from the first two statements is that language can go beyond thoughts into the realm of nonsense, but we have thoughts which language can't articulate with all its words and dictionaries. So why this dual contradiction? Let's explore!

The first two sentences. Carefully think of each. Can you think of a colorless green vapor? It’s a logical negation. An impossibility. However, nonsensical statements are surely possible, but what picture it produces in your mind? The weight of your voice? This effect is called a language illusion, which in our ordinary lives is not so explicit. Ludwig Wittgenstein, a logician philosopher claimed that all philosophy beyond scientific statements belonged to this realm of ‘non-sense’. This doesn’t mean that Language has a one up on thoughts since it encompasses thoughts and nonsense, but there are thoughts which are outside the ambit of language as well.

Consider this thought experiment (also attributed to Wittgenstein). Suppose you have two people, each with an identical white box, and an object inside which we assume to be different, which the other can’t see. (we call the people A and B and the objects X and Y respectively) A looks at X, thinks it’s a beetle and announces that he has a ‘beetle’. The beetle in A and B’s dictionary is called Z, so the box represents Z. That means, B looks at Y, thinks it’s a beetle and announces Z, which is his identical box. Both A and B use the same box, that is the word, but here comes the interesting part. The objects X and Y can be anything, either both beetles, beetle looking wasps, or something else, which they both call beetle but can’t see the fundamental distinction between X and Y, and hence thought gains a one up on Language. So when we use words such as <em>love, justice, </em>and freedom, different forms exist in different people with some similarities, but usually more different than we presume.

What is a chair? When you picture a chair, the familiar cushioned four legged furniture item comes to mind. However, a flat rock or a flat tree trunk are chairs? So a chair is something or anything we can sit on? Defined by its use? This presents a problem. Then what is a human being? Is a fetus a human being when it is not sentient nor looks like us? Then how come a fetus enjoys more human rights than say a chimpanzee? Our genetically closest being?

But one of my favorite language puzzles is sarcasm. It’s amazing on our ability to identify someone’s true meaning in some unrelated statement, sometimes the exact opposite of that meaning itself, and above that, the sarcastic person doesn’t try to make it any obvious of his sarcasm, as we know skill here is to be as subtle as possible, but what then divides the line of a true intentioned meaning and sarcasm, and how are we so good at detecting it?

So if B hurts itself and A asks, ‘Are you hurt?’ and B replies ‘No, I feel fabulous’ means the opposite. Thought gains one up on Language here, since the context becomes relevant. How important this is can be judged in AI, and how AI would recognize sarcasm in the future.

Similarly, reading between the lines, implied thoughts such as Netflix and Chilling which neither has to do anything with Netflix nor Chilling per se, but is used nonetheless. The question then is, why not be logically correct? Replying to Are you hurt a straight Yes or I would like to have sex with you, are not used because of the earlier language box example. Netflix and Chill can be a box which can either be X, I want to have sex with you, or Y, I really want to Netflix and Chill. B here can’t tell whether A Means X or Y, while A knows B can choose X or Y, and if chooses Y, it’s a safety outlet to mean that No, I do not want to have sex with you. These are the Language Games we play daily without even realizing it.

This leads to a final section on why it’s not all that bad to be obfuscatory in a complex argument. Suppose an author has in his mind an idea X, which he wants his audience to get as he conceives of it. The expert then uses language in such a way that he projects X through a combination of words Y, which the receiver decodes easily, with minimum effort and retains the original signal X. But an expert is not a computer. An expert can be a poet, which is the ultimate form of aesthetic enjoyment in decoding a signal, but say this expert first distorts his idea X intentionally into X’, which contains fragments of X along with other structural distortions, which are also not intentionally encoded, but the expert is fully aware of this. We call this a mutation, and though this mutation can be anything, the expert has some idea on ways this can be decoded. The reader then struggles with the decoding process. Y reveals fragments of X', but these fragments are not enough to form coherence, so here B adds his own data to X’’(what he gets from X’ fragments). B then completes the picture to (X’’+D) which we call B’s Interpretation of Y, as it makes sense to B’s life. The expert is somebody who is knowingly good at this process.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>85</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-09-02 14:33:02</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-09-02 14:33:02</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>language-thoughts-metaphors-and-analogies</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[8883961877]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10212416042048606";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The Behavioral Revolution in Economics</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/10/13/the-behavioral-revolution-in-economics/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 10:49:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=99</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-106" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009.jpg" alt="ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009" width="1449" height="1083" />

Prof. Richard Thaler, The Recipient of The Nobel Prize in Economics, 2017

When I first started studying Economics in college, I naturally assumed that economics is behavioral. In fact, that’s how I learned and internalized the concepts of diminishing returns, diminishing marginal utility, economies of scale, the laws of demand and supply et al. Of course at the time I didn’t know that such concepts fuelled a deeper purpose, of concave functions in convex sets being open to well behaved mathematical analysis. In hindsight, I do remember things which flummoxed me at the time, when I really thought, who really equates marginal revenue with marginal costs in a business? I’ve never heard of someone run a business like that! But of course, since I was an Indian student, and a fresher in Economics, I cast the thoughts away and thought well, this is how it must be and the businesses are naïve, after all, they haven’t done formal training in Economics!

&nbsp;

After about seven years since those days, now well settled into my Ph.D. in the subject, I have really come a long way in thinking about things. The evolution has been bumpy, and now I can say that my puberty is over regarding the field. I’d like to think it works for all students the same way. You start with your own intuitions about the field at the start. The introductory textbooks restrict your domain so that you are ashamed of your earlier ideas, and lack of confidence in saying that this theory doesn’t make any sense. I mean look at the mathematics! They must be right. It’s me who’s stupid, and we start speaking in the language of the textbooks.

&nbsp;

However, when this period is over if one is brave enough to consider graduate school, you start deconstructing the subject according to your own ways. After formal methods become second nature to you, you start gaining more and more confidence, until you someday are able to say. ‘The mathematics is fine. But why would someone put such conditions as to expect the answer?’. It’s kind of like driving. It just makes sense after a particular point of time, and though you still argue in your head that ‘I know nothing.’ The fact is that you do know now, and soon you’ll become that author other students would balk at.

&nbsp;

An interesting part here is that when this evolution takes place, the learning consists of many elements. You start appreciating as to why that author made those unintuitive assumptions. Tractability, feasibility and the application of models start making sense to you. A certain philosophical understanding accompanies the technical understanding, and as you read more and more, the jigsaw puzzle starts solving itself, and one can see that puzzle from micro specificity to at the broadest possible sense. But still, one thing remains unchanged. That curious intuitive child who questions, like he did seven years back, although now with better tools and formal methods as ammunition.

&nbsp;

This leads me back to my example of Behavioral Economics. The first question that bothered me were certain assumptions which made no sense. So now you saw work which actually challenged those assumptions, and won a Nobel Prize for that. But it is important and liberating to know that Economics was at a time the most open field for all sorts of ideas. In fact, the first Behavioral Economist was none other than our own Mr. Adam Smith, with his somewhat lesser known title, <strong>The Theory of Moral Sentiments. </strong>Not just Smith, other intellectual titans such as F.A. Hayek, who published again a lesser known work called <strong>The Sensory Order, </strong>and another titan, John Maynard Keynes, whose lack of formal economic training meant that most of his perspectives on economic thought were intuitive. Animal Spirits, Liquidity Trap, The Beauty Contest Games, and so much more. We were all behavioral until we decided to become Scientists and not Social Scientists, which happened mostly in the second half of the twentieth century onwards.

&nbsp;

Coming to the Nobel winning Behavioral Economist who started a new revolution. No, I’m not talking about Richard Thaler, who won this year’s prize, I am talking about a genius by the name of Herbert Simon, who won the prize in 1978, for attacking the most controversial and important assumptions Behavioral Economics owe their career to, <strong>Rationality. </strong>Any academician apart from economists will laugh at the assumption so fundamental to economic analysis that humans behave rationally in markets, at least statistically. That means, we see our lifetime’s worth of benefits from one good when buying it. That given the same option again and again over time, there is no option that we should change it. That we perfectly calculate each extra benefit from the good to each dollar paid for it. Of course, this is horseradish. We basically need this assumption to perform mathematical analysis with good continuous functions and an equilibrium point. Simon worked on what we call Bounded Rationality.

&nbsp;

Maurice Allais worked on the consistency axiom and showed us how the framing of choices can deceive us. Vernon Smith helped develop the field of experimental economics, where microeconomic axioms could be tested under controlled settings. Alvin Roth worked on the market design, where not everything depends on prices. (Price gouging makes perfect sense to an economist, but would never be legally justified, rightly so). Kahneman and Tversky worked on Prospect Theory, that depending on the amount of reward or punishment, our valuation, and expected utility changes, and is not constant, of course, we don’t all have iron hearts!

&nbsp;

So far so good. These gentlemen gave us great works and deservedly got published in the top journals, and won a Nobel prize at that. But they weren’t a threat to the established industry. These analyses were great for a moment’s reflection and then getting back to work. Until the tide grew larger and larger, and Richard Thaler was one of the few forerunners of this new wave. This needs to go mainstream these forerunners thought, which had genuine scholars as well as opportunists who’ll get a wealth of new research to publish. Thaler’s work on Mental Accounting and other behavioral anomalies and collaboration with Kahneman and Tversky, and upcoming students who wanted a more psychological approach to economics struggled for almost two decades until the line of work got its own handbook, it’s own journal and its own foundation. It helped that this community was tightly knit, unlike the dispersed nature of the neoclassical school, which was divided on matters of how much should the markets be free. The Harvard-MIT intellectuals versus the Chicago School.

&nbsp;

Behavioral Economics gained its biggest breakthrough in the financial crisis when according to me, this subfield gained the most acceptability and was much more attractive than Marxian critiques of the crises, and suddenly Behavioral Economics became the rage. Together with Behavioral Finance, which challenged the rational Efficient Market Hypothesis, the popularity of Behavioral Economics skyrocketed, and though Behavioral Economics gained the name, the popularity had its own trade-off, and one aspect shined brighter than most: - ‘Nudging’. Thaler got his own cameo in the movie ‘The Big Short’, other behavioral economists were called into policy making to make simple nudge incentives, which on accord of their own incentives they most definitely complied. Behavioral Economics as a buzzword became more and more obscure and handed an opportunity for the criticizers on a golden plate. It’s easy to see whenever a research framework clicks, opportunists jump at making all sorts of theories and predictions, just as econometrics is currently struggling. The abuse of that framework makes us ask, is it the theory at fault? No! It’s human behavior! Econometrics and Behavioral economics if done robustly are extremely useful to develop precise descriptions and predictions. It is unto the academic community and those stakeholders at peer-reviewed journals to face this monumental task of sifting through the hay to find the needle.

&nbsp;

The future of economic theory depends much on how computing technology updates and allows us to perform trillions of calculations so that models need not be so restricted anymore. Agent-based simulations with multiple assumptions in base could be tested for innumerable parameters again and again with varied assumptions on behavior. It’s time to keep the future in mind in how economics would be done, and my wishful thinking gains confidence by the decision of the Nobel committee to recognize the role Behavioral Economics would have in the future.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>99</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-10-13 10:49:44</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-10-13 10:49:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>the-behavioral-revolution-in-economics</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10212719249788610";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[10278233854]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/10/13/the-behavioral-revolution-in-economics/ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 10:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>106</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-10-13 10:48:44</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-10-13 10:48:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>99</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/10/ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:1449;s:6:"height";i:1083;s:4:"file";s:124:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/10/ct-nobel-prize-economics-richard-thaler-20171009.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:119015;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 09:39:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>114</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 09:39:07</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 09:39:07</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:612;s:6:"height";i:408;s:4:"file";s:108:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:176518;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>soundmagic-e10c-4-3</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/soundmagic-e10c-4-3/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 09:47:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/soundmagic-e10c-4-3.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>115</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 09:47:38</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 09:47:38</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>soundmagic-e10c-4-3</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/soundmagic-e10c-4-3.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/soundmagic-e10c-4-3.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:616;s:6:"height";i:347;s:4:"file";s:95:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/soundmagic-e10c-4-3.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:40919;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>41gfqxe5obl-_sl500_ac_ss350_</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/41gfqxe5obl-_sl500_ac_ss350_/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 09:50:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/41gfqxe5obl-_sl500_ac_ss350_.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[AudioTechnica M40X]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>116</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 09:50:20</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 09:50:20</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>41gfqxe5obl-_sl500_ac_ss350_</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/41gfqxe5obl-_sl500_ac_ss350_.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/41gfqxe5obl-_sl500_ac_ss350_.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:350;s:6:"height";i:350;s:4:"file";s:104:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/41gfqxe5obl-_sl500_ac_ss350_.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:16683;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>SAMSUNG CSC</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/samsung-csc/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 09:51:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/7404928.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[SAMSUNG CSC]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[HM5 pads]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>117</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 09:51:25</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 09:51:25</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>samsung-csc</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/7404928.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/7404928.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:5472;s:6:"height";i:3648;s:4:"file";s:83:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/7404928.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"5";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:5:"NX300";s:7:"caption";s:11:"SAMSUNG CSC";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:10:"1432655965";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:2:"42";s:3:"iso";s:3:"200";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:6:"0.0125";s:5:"title";s:11:"SAMSUNG CSC";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"1";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:2516848;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 09:54:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>118</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 09:54:45</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 09:54:45</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:1024;s:6:"height";i:768;s:4:"file";s:114:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:15:"BlackBerry 9700";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"1";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:97424;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 09:57:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>119</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 09:57:24</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 09:57:24</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:345;s:6:"height";i:450;s:4:"file";s:95:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:19673;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Confessions of an Audiophile</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 10:23:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=113</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-114" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d.jpg" alt="440e9075b9818b003e793dfd1e05806d" width="612" height="408" />

There are various ways you can define an Audiophile, either as a badge of honor, a self-proclaimed title, a derogatory term for a snob who has tons of money to waste, as you’ll find so on the interweb. Even among audiophiles, this judgment is present, and more strongly so, as the snobs will themselves consider many within the community to be audio-fools rather than audiophiles, regressing the irony further.

So what is an audiophile? And what is my part in all of this? And why am I bothering the readers with an introduction to this niche community?

An Audiophile, in the truest sense, is someone who enjoys or is obsessed with accurate sound reproduction, mostly applied to the music industry. The simple point is that in the process of production of music to consumption of it, we tend to miss out on details either from induced noise and distortion, poor equipment, compression, and so on. This post is an entry to this strange world so that anyone can benefit from the wisdom of the community with the least amount of foolery. I consider myself an audiophile simply because of my love of music, and I don’t mind spending at least some money more than average to enjoy one of the great joys of life. I have spent months going through various audiophile communities, and I can say enough to give my opinion which might help you understand the rationality and the irrationality of the community.

<strong>Disclosure: The world of Audiophiles is a slippery slope, and one can simply fall into the cycle of getting more equipment than needed, and this is not an exaggeration. So I suggest not going very deep into it, unless you are a music producer, or have lakhs of rupees to spend.</strong>

So let’s start with the basics, which starts with the physics of sound. The sound is generated by the rapid compression and decompression of air molecules, which have a frequency. This vibration takes the form of a wave. Our voice to the drums to strings of a guitar and all instruments work on this principle. The sound wave reaches our ear-drums or a microphone, which vibrates accordingly to the compressions of air, producing electric signals, leading to our perception of the sound. The average human ear can hear frequencies from 20 Hertz to 20,000 Hertz.
<h1><strong>The Source</strong></h1>
In the studio, the music produced is picked up by high-quality microphones, and electrically stored as .wav files, and recorded into various storage devices such as the vinyl or cassette in analog form. These .wav files are raw files and usually are suited for studio mixing and remastering since each wave file can be massive, and unpractical for portable use.

The analog wave is then converted into a digital format and compressed using various technologies. The most popular one is, of course, the mp3 file, which is an example of lossy compression. The basic point is that the algorithm for an mp3 file simply cuts out all frequencies below and beyond the human range, and masks out other, usually inaudible or barely audible sounds to present a file of magnitudes of smaller size. The mp3 files also differ in the amount of information cut from the original file, and while the ubiquitous 128 kbps is fine for streaming services, the 320 kbps is larger and more applicable for critical listening.

Audiophiles usually prefer the analog reproduction though if possible, that is the vinyl, or the DVD of an album, for digital music, they prefer lossless conversion formats such as .flac files, which are much larger than an mp3 file but retains all of the subsonic and supersonic frequencies.

<strong>Verdict #1 – I suggest that if one doesn’t have high fidelity audio equipment, and just wants to do some casual listening then low bit rate mp3s are fine. But I highly suggest that for critical listening and using good audio equipment, 320 kbps mp3 files and FLAC files are a must, at least for the albums you really love, and the classics such as Kind of Blue by Miles Davis or The Dark Side of the Moon by Pink Floyd. I would expand a bit more on this when I come to equipment.</strong><strong> </strong>
<h1><strong>The Reproduction</strong><strong> </strong></h1>
The next part is the reverse. Now we need to convert the digital files stored on your smartphone or laptop to your equipment. I will focus on headphones for this post since they offer the highest fidelity in the least amount of money and convenience. The vinyl or the DVDs usually have to be used with a hi-fi stereo system, which I might do in another post. There are three parts to reproduction.

<strong>Digital to Analog conversion – </strong>Speakers are reverse microphones. They receive electric signals and a diaphragm vibrates, compressing the air and producing sound. It’s obvious that your speakers don’t read 0s and 1s as what your computer stores the files as. All smartphones and laptops have a built-in DAC, called a Digital to Analog converter. In India, we simply call them sound cards. Now though your onboard DAC is usually good enough for casual listening, when listening to high-quality files with high-quality equipment, we can run into some trouble.

A really good headphone can pick up frequency ranges a lot larger than our hearing capability. Coupled with a good quality source file, a lesser quality DAC will reproduce signals which would have induced noise and distortion, which would be easily picked up by your headphones, hampering your experience. The point is that in the analog to digital conversion by studios, it is obvious they use the highest quality equipment to prevent noise and distortion, but the reproduction of the reverse is our responsibility to bear. However, this is contentious because the modern day onboard DACs are improving in quality so that external DAC which are cheaper might go redundant. So unless you have really good headphones, the DAC can be thought about over time, depending on your satisfaction with the music.
<h1><strong>Headphones </strong></h1>
Coming to the most important part of the audiophile discussion. Let’s start with the basics of types of Headphones. I’m going to assume that the fit is of the over the ears variety which offers the best in terms of comfort and quality, with portability being the trade-off. But before that, we need to go through some basic terminologies used in the world of head-fi.

<strong>Open vs Closed –</strong> Open back headphones have ear cups which are covered by grills on the outer side, which effectively means that your headphones are no longer isolated from the outside world. This means that not only will the sound of your headphones leak outside, but you won’t be insulated from the outside environment at all. Closed back headphones are fully covered on the outside, providing the necessary isolation.

So why would anyone buy open backed headphones? Well, they are open for a reason. The openness of the cans gives you an airy and a more natural feel towards the music. It provides scope for a much larger soundstage as if one is hearing to the music live. The closed back as is obvious, provides isolation, doesn’t disturb others, and is usually stated to have scope for a larger bass response than the open cans.

<strong>Sound Signature – </strong>Every headphone sounds different, but for an audiophile, it is imperative to know what the difference is, and what the music should really sound like. Now it is known that most cheap earphones and some branded <strong>cough</strong> Beats <strong>cough</strong> headphones are geared towards bass. Audiophiles have two issues regarding this. It is not that Audiophiles don’t love their bass, but the bass from cheap quality sets is what is called a muddy bass, or uncontrolled bass. Audiophiles love the tightness in their music, and a controlled bass even though less in magnitude, is high in quality. The second is that Audiophiles by definition, want a neutral sound signature. The easiest way to visualize this is that each headphone has its own adjusted Equalizer settings, which one can’t change. This invisible equalizer is the sound signature. When the equalizer is flat or off, we deem it as neutral, which many of us might know can seem boring to the untrained, but over time, one extracts a purer sound, just as the artists wanted us to hear it. Audiophiles though are not always interested in listening to music critically or analytically, pointing out each individual notes, and hence there are also V-shaped signature phones, which means an elevated bass and treble response, which is more fatiguing to the ear but much more fun.

<strong> </strong><strong>Driver Technology – </strong>There are three technologies through which sound is reproduced. The most popular ones mostly in all headphones below Rs. 30,000 are dynamic drivers. There is also a planar magnetic technology, which is heavy and offers much warmer and powerful bass response, and at the highest levels are electrostatic headphones, which use capacitive technology and need extremely high voltages to drive them.

<strong>Frequency Response – </strong>Though humans have a hearing range of 20 Hz to 20kHz, premium headphones offer a frequency response from 5 Hz to 40 kHz. When one hears a lossless file, the waves corresponding to such frequencies are not truncated, and premium headphones do pick these waves up. This means that even if a bass frequency is more than 20 Hz, there might be a layered sound picked up from premium headphones. These are not necessarily audible, but subjectively it almost always makes a difference. Powerful headphones also pick up the faintest of sounds one might have never heard due to either a colored response, where the bass, mids, and trebles are off balance. A neutral headphone then would not sacrifice that background rhythm guitar or percussion for the vocals (usually mids or lower treble). Almost all audiophile headphones have a generated frequency response curve which can be googled and depending on one’s preferences and genres.

<strong>Miscellaneous – </strong>One major aspect of audiophile headphones that cannot be overlooked are the impedance parameters of the headphones. Now impedance is simply the resistance of the coils to the electric current, and hence impedance is measured in <strong>Ohms</strong>. The lower the impedance, the easier it is to pass the current or to drive the headphones, which means it becomes easier to power them, by even a smartphone. However, many audiophile and monitoring headphones come in high impedance parameters since they are meant for use in studio mixing or equipment which have a built-in amplifier so that a lower impedance would result in the headphones being driven too easily. A kind of analogy might be driving a car on a lower gear to a higher gear. The low geared car if over accelerated will put stress on the engine and even total it. For optimum performance, the right shifting needs to be done. High impedance headphones usually above 100 ohms will be underpowered through a smartphone or a laptop, and produce poor quality low volume output. Such headphones require a dedicated headphone amplifier is used with a portable device, which will give justice to their price.

The second aspect is the soundstage. When we hear through normal headphones, it feels as if the sound is being played inside our head. But audiophile headphones, especially open backed ones have a soundstage so that when you hear through the headphones, it gives an illusion as if the sound is coming through actual speakers, with spatial effects for each instrument, and it feels that the sound is coming from around our head. This is much more fun, and also helps one to precisely pinpoint each instrument playing rather than a muddled mess, and hence suited for analytical or critical listening.

<strong>MY VERDICT </strong><strong> </strong>

I think most aspects at least for the beginner audiophile has been covered, and this section will fill out the practical gaps. The most important thing which is reiterated on all genuine audiophile forums is that you can be one at <strong>ANY BUDGET. </strong>So this will be a list of my recommendations at every budget point. The Audiophile hobby is a lifelong one, and though there are impulses to buy better amps or headphones, I would suggest the orthodox audiophile journey.

<strong>You would need at least one pair of Earphones, and one set of open backed and one set of closed back headphones. At the beginner stage, you can start with earphones and one closed cans. Only buy Amps when you reach the second stage of beginner audiophiles, and perhaps DACs when you reach the mid-fi stage.</strong>
<h2><strong>Earphones/IEMs</strong></h2>
<strong>Starting Game</strong>

This is the sub 1k genre, this is what the audio enthusiasts start with, and the good news is that even in this group, one can find earphones with noticeable quality improvements over stock buds. I think that it’s not worthwhile to get Sennheiser or Sony products at this range, and from the countless earphones I’ve tried, I’d recommend getting a Soundmagic e18, Creative ep 630 or JBLs.

<strong>Mid Game</strong>

This should be your default setting unless one is really into earphones. The RHA S500, Beyerdynamic Byron, Sennheiser CX series, Soundmagic e10, e50 or e80 are some of the best in this category. Try to look for an earphone with lots of ear tips, good warranty, sturdy build and tangle free cables.

&nbsp;

[caption id="attachment_115" align="alignnone" width="616"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-115" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/soundmagic-e10c-4-3.jpg" alt="soundmagic-e10c-4-3" width="616" height="347" /> The Soundmagic E10C[/caption]

&nbsp;

<strong>End Game</strong>

I am yet to reach this stage, but someday I’ll definitely think of getting some Shure’s IEMs which definitely would be my endgame. Please skip Bose products which are only good for sound cancellation. If you’re really into it, I would suggest having a look at Audeze’s IEMs
<h2><strong>Closed Cans</strong><strong> </strong></h2>
<strong>Starting Game</strong>

I highly recommend starting with Audio Technica’s M40xs, and rather than buying the more popular M50xs, you can use m40xs with some HM5 pads and have a better product. The m40x is much more neutral, and the pads very comfortable, unlike the fatiguing comfort and in your face bass and treble of the m50s.

[gallery ids="116,117" type="square" columns="2"]

&nbsp;

<strong>Mid Game</strong>

If one has decided to keep two headphones, I highly recommend having a look at the Beyerdynamic dt770 pros, which come in three versions. Skip the 32 ohms one. These are a unique set of cans and offer excellent comfort, both in weight and the pads. One of the most comfortable headphones I’ve owned, and though these are studio monitor headphones, these have a V-shaped sound, but the Bass is amazingly awesome. I have not heard a better bass response on my electronic or Heavy Metal tracks and is very much controlled. The 80 ohms are the ones I recommend since they offer a better bass and slightly less treble. The 250 ohms’ version is the more standard one for recording, but it has, even more, treble in a phone already high in it, which can be piercing to some ears. The 600 ohms’ version would require HUGE amplification, and I won’t recommend that, though all three versions require a dedicated amp, the 80 ohms version can do with an entry level amp like the fiio e10k.

&nbsp;

[caption id="attachment_118" align="alignnone" width="1024"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-118" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958.jpg" alt="beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro-32-ohms-459958" width="1024" height="768" /> Beyerdynamic DT770 Pros[/caption]

&nbsp;

&nbsp;

<strong>End Game</strong>

Again still I’m stuck in the mid-fi category, I’m more than happy with these closed cans, and would perhaps only upgrade my open set. The Beyerdynamic dt1770 has been released and has all the goods of the dt770s with so much more.
<h2><strong>Open Cans</strong></h2>
<strong>Starting Game</strong>

Now we come to the Sennheisers, who specialize in open cans. The Sennheiser HD series are some of the most neutral and amazing headphones you can buy. I highly recommend buying the HD598 Special edition series, or other variants in Sennheiser’s HD 5xx series if you can get them for cheap. The HD598 is THE MOST COMFORTABLE HEADPHONE I’VE EVER PUT ON. The sound is balanced, the bass isn’t too bad, the mids are exceptional, and the trebles are high but not as much as the Beyers. You can listen to them for hours without fatigue and can be driven without an amp, though a fiio can definitely help. Try to get a used one since these are the ones you’ll want to upgrade, I know I would, now I’ve tasted the truth of true audiophile sound.

&nbsp;

[caption id="attachment_119" align="aligncenter" width="355"]<img class="  wp-image-119 aligncenter" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_.jpg" alt="41x8zpjlkjl-_sy450_" width="355" height="463" /> Sennheiser HD598 SR[/caption]

&nbsp;

<strong>Mid Game</strong>

The Philips Fidelio X2 series are some of the highest recommended phones. But my lifetime mid-fis would be again, the Sennheisers. Now the Sennheiser HD 600 and HD 650 are LEGENDARY headphones. Audio is something which suffers from diminishing returns, so when you buy a decent headphone from a cheap one, there is usually a world of difference, but the more money you keep on throwing, the difference would be marginal, and ultimately just a different type of sound, so it’s your decision on finding the optimal stopping point. But even if the HD600 and HD650s might offer a 15% improvement over the already stellar HD598s, then, why not? Given that they come at the same price as Bose’s QC35, which is at the same price, or even hi-fi systems, one can definitely get some exceptionally good headphones at the price. Maybe I’m biased. But these are notorious for their high (300 ohms) impedance and require some god research(not a typo) on the amps which will drive them, though you can’t go wrong with a Schiit stack(pronounced SHIT).

&nbsp;

[caption id="attachment_121" align="alignnone" width="750"]<strong><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-121" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/1-1.jpg" alt="1-1" width="750" height="425" /></strong> <strong>Massdrop's Sennheiser HD 6xx, a revamped version of the HD650s</strong>[/caption]

&nbsp;

<strong>End Game</strong>

<strong>LOL. </strong>I don’t know. I’ve reserved my endgame to a distant point in life as of now. But if I were given a gift to choose, Beyerdynamic T1, Sennheiser HD800 S, Hifiman 1000, Audeze LCD 3s, Stax, etc. If you’re willing to spend in this range( a lakh or more I’ll assume you already know much more than me), so enjoy, and yes, I understand you, unless you’re spending your dad’s money on them, then tch tch. Buy your beats.

&nbsp;

[caption id="attachment_122" align="alignnone" width="1000"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-122" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/audeze_epk-july_2012-6.jpg" alt="audeze_epk-july_2012-6" width="1000" height="782" /> Audeze's LCD 3, retailing at above Rs 1 lakh are Planar magnetic headphones[/caption]

&nbsp;

Online communities such as Reddit’s Headphone community, Head-fi, ZeosPantera reviews have a lot of details if you’re interested in further research.

&nbsp;

[caption id="attachment_123" align="alignnone" width="580"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-123" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/stax_lambda_1.jpg" alt="stax_lambda_1" width="580" height="618" /> STAX Lambda series Electrostatic headphones. These are definitely endgame.[/caption]

&nbsp;
<h1><strong>Amplifier</strong></h1>
<strong> </strong>Amplifiers are present in all stereo sound systems. Whenever there is equipment dealing with high impedances, as in any high-quality system described above, the output current is low means the volume would not be sufficient to do the headphones justice. There are, of course, digital amplifier programs on your computer, but akin to a physical amplifier being like an optical zoom, the digital one is digital zoom, and we all know how digital zoom distorts the photograph. Same with sound. Dedicated Headphone amps would help get the proper juice (read power) to your headphones by amplifying the sound wave without distortion. Nothing much needs to be said for amps other than the usual rule of thumb so here it goes.

<strong>MY VERDICT</strong>

The Fiio e10k is an integrated DAC and amp which would suit the id fi game, until you deal with the Sennheiser 600 and above, after which you would require a much better amp. The only upgrade I can suggest which I think would not be wasteful is the popular Schiit Stack, that is the Schiit Modi amp and the Schiit Magni DAC. Tube amps are beyond my stage at present, but I shall keep updating.

[gallery ids="124,125" type="columns"]
<h1><strong>Conclusion</strong></h1>
Even at such a length, I’ve barely scratched the surface of Audiophilia, but at least now you can jump on the boat. From my analysis, the basic setup shall do you just fine for years until you upgrade or even if you don’t, they’re awesome enough.
<h2><strong>Audiophile Starter kit</strong><strong> </strong></h2>
<strong>Soundmagic E10c earphones – Rs. 1400</strong>

<strong>Audio Technica- ATH m40x closed headphones – Rs 7000(with hm5 pads- 8000)</strong>

<strong>Sennheiser hd598s – Rs. 8000</strong>

<strong>Fiio E10k DAC+AMP –  Rs. 5000</strong>

<strong>Approximately Rs. 23,000 will give you one of the best investments you can make if you love music.</strong>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>113</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 10:23:06</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 10:23:06</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>confessions-of-an-audiophile</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10212998854658557";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[11634558321]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>9325339</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/attachment/9325339/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 10:01:05 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/9325339.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>120</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 10:01:05</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 10:01:05</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>9325339</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/9325339.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/9325339.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:507;s:6:"height";i:338;s:4:"file";s:83:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/9325339.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:40263;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1-1</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/1-1/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 10:02:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/1-1.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>121</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 10:02:44</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 10:02:44</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>1-1</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/1-1.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/1-1.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:750;s:6:"height";i:425;s:4:"file";s:79:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/1-1.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:308984;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>audeze_epk-july_2012-6</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/audeze_epk-july_2012-6/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 10:04:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/audeze_epk-july_2012-6.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>122</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 10:04:31</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 10:04:31</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>audeze_epk-july_2012-6</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/audeze_epk-july_2012-6.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/audeze_epk-july_2012-6.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:1000;s:6:"height";i:782;s:4:"file";s:98:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/audeze_epk-july_2012-6.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"1";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:862495;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>stax_lambda_1</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/stax_lambda_1/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 10:07:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/stax_lambda_1.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>123</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 10:07:52</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 10:07:52</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>stax_lambda_1</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/stax_lambda_1.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/stax_lambda_1.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:580;s:6:"height";i:618;s:4:"file";s:89:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/stax_lambda_1.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:109183;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>dsc_0765</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/dsc_0765/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 10:09:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/dsc_0765.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Fiio e10k USB DAC AMP]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>124</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 10:09:31</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 10:09:31</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>dsc_0765</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/dsc_0765.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/dsc_0765.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:600;s:6:"height";i:319;s:4:"file";s:84:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/dsc_0765.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:34282;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>maxresdefault</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2017/11/20/confessions-of-an-audiophile/maxresdefault/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 10:10:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/maxresdefault.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[SCHIIT STACK. MAGNI and MODI]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>125</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2017-11-20 10:10:15</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2017-11-20 10:10:15</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>maxresdefault</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>113</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2017/11/maxresdefault.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/maxresdefault.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:4096;s:6:"height";i:2304;s:4:"file";s:89:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2017/11/maxresdefault.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:323802;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>A Quixotic Research Proposal in Economic Theory</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2018/02/17/a-quixotic-research-proposal-in-economic-theory/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 07:39:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=127</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[It has been three months since I last posted, despite my racing mind churning all sorts of ideas as I keep reading and realizing that Socrates was the wisest man in knowing that 'We can know nothing'. The last three months were spent in trying to brainstorm enough to pop out a proposal someone like me would deem as my magnum opus in research. Alas, I floated a little too much and produced a piece which I can just say was, umm, controversial. My proposal for a Ph.D. level research was rejected and I was given a month to produce an entirely different proposal with three questions, and after working like a horse and drinking gallons of coffee, I have managed to make a decent proposal which would be passed and satisfies me as well. It took enormous efforts to put my ideas and dilute them to make them amenable to how conventional economic theoretical research is done. Though as I will continue to fulfill the label I have been given by my colleagues and faculty as the idealistic rebel, it will be much more veiled now, as I have learned in these past few weeks. The original ideas are something I feel very personal about, and I mean it when I say that it's just not "Reason", but an instinct which screams that 'DO IT' but unfortunately that's not how Academia works.

I will produce a sort of summary of what my doctoral dissertation planned at, and will cement it so that years later when I read this piece, I simultaneously laugh and be embarrassed, but equally proud, that a twenty-five-year-old boy dared to go beyond the box, and failed, but tried again after years, failed again, and eventually got enough of a name to work on it finally.

Here is the proposal's synopsis for you to enjoy and perhaps laugh or balk at, but just take it as some food for thought that 'what if'? I'm sorry for the technicalities, though I tried to be as lucid as I could.
<h1><strong>LANGUAGE COMMUNICATION AND ECONOMIC THEORY</strong></h1>
<div class="page" title="Page 1">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

Economics as a discipline has epistemologically two roles in the present and upcoming decades, i.e. of probing and answering questions of economic affairs, and second, and more abstractly, as a mode of tools and analysis to better understand a broader set of ideas across disciplines. The latter means it is flexible enough to absorb elements from other sciences and social sciences, which has already become apparent in the fields of Evolutionary Biology, Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning, and the focus of the dissertation, Information Theory and Linguistics (including Philosophy of Language). This intermingling of disciplines makes both fields better off, where linguists can take advantage of strategic interaction, optimality, and efficiency results while we can incorporate theories of communication and language from them. It is my personal opinion that the world is offered to us as it is, the fields are artificially constructed and in their rigidity, we miss out on some potentially important discoveries. It is with an optimistic observation of seeing the walls among disciplines break, that has inspired me to work on a dissertation across disciplines.
<div class="page" title="Page 1">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

Language is the mechanism through which humans communicate. Without some form of Language, no interaction at the present scale of economic affairs would have been conceivable. Not only do we communicate in language, but we also think and learn in terms of language (Whorf – 1956; Wittgenstein – 1921). Economics despite its affirmation as the ‘Queen of Social Sciences’ has neglected to delve into linguistic effects on economic behavior. The Present treatment of communication has also been fairly recent, with Spence’s theory of costly signaling, and game theoretic models of costless signaling, after the seminal work of Crawford and Sobel (1982) and follow up literature dubbed as Cheap Talk games. The framework of these games have their roots in Lewis’ Sender-Receiver games (1969) where the sender observes a state, sends a message, the receiver takes the action conditional on the message which affects both their payoffs. Many leading economists as well as from the outside have voiced concerns of treating communication among humans in a model of ‘Animal Communication’ (Lipman – 2009; Rubinstein – 2000) the primary argument of which is that such games are mostly concerned with the strategies associated with a message rather than the content of the message which under a linguistic signal can have varying effects apart from what the papers suggest.
<div class="page" title="Page 1">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

With the aforementioned motivations in mind, my dissertation would be a compilation of essays on classic problems of Microeconomic theory with language as the mode of analysis. Since Language and Linguistics are as broad a field as Economics and deals with subject matters relating to Speech Patterns, Etymology, Sociolinguistics, it is to be made clear at the outset that before such an analysis, a theory needs to be established to make concepts from such theories amenable to economic analysis. This means two things: -
<div class="page" title="Page 1">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

1. Language, as studied in ‘Language and Economics’ domain under cultural and social economics, a survey for which is given by Grin (2009), deals with sociolinguistic aspects of language in economic life, for example, differential wages of Francophones and Anglophones. However, the treatment of language in my dissertation would be a complete abstraction of language, drawn from linguistic philosophy to conceive of a language which can refer to a natural language, an artificial language, or even a nonexistent language abstraction, as the analysis deems fit.
<div class="page" title="Page 2">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

2. Though my proposed dissertation is closer in spirit to Marshack (1965) and Rubinstein (2000), who have tried to analyze aspects of Language efficiency and analysis through economic methods, it is not what my dissertation proposes to study. The work which is closest to my objectives is “Is Language vague” (Lipman, 2009), but as discussed above, it provides a framework developed in the style of Cheap Talk literature, and itself concludes that the quirks of linguistic effects on information transmission can at best be studied within a boundedly rational model.

<strong>DISSERTATION OUTLINE</strong>
<div class="page" title="Page 2">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

The first section of the dissertation would outline aspects from linguistic theory to define an abstract conception of language, and how it relates to notions of data, information, knowledge, technical proficiency, wisdom and practical usage. It will elucidate how language can treat these processes relatively to signaling theory. For a formalization of language, it is imperative to be aware that this is not an end but a means to study market outcomes and behavior, and hence only aspects of linguistics which are general and applicable would be used for analysis. Philosophy of language is useful in this aspect, particularly those of the philosopher Ludwig Wittgenstein, notwithstanding some of the most insightful views of language but also because his work transitioned from a purely logical conception of language in his early work (Wittgenstein - 1922 ), to the strict rejection and more naturalistic view of it in his later work (Wittgenstein - 1953). The formalization of the two models would provide us with the option of comparing statics to providing a dynamic model of language evolution1 from the former to the latter, and its welfare effects on the market participants. Other aspects of Language philosophy and Linguistics would be borrowed from the works of Pierce, de Saussure, Chomsky, Frege, Russell, and others to create a simple but hybrid conception of language which embodies information and knowledge within its structure.
<div class="page" title="Page 2">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

After the conception of a linguistic model for economic agents, the dissertation will apply it to three classic problems in Information Economics literature (though other fields are not yet excluded). The following sections will cover each of these.

<strong>THE MARKET FOR EXPERT SERVICES</strong>
<div class="page" title="Page 2">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

Certain markets for expert services such as for medical treatment, legal consultation, car repair, financial services etc. pose problems on account of the large information asymmetries between the sellers(experts) and the consumers. Darby and Karni(1973) labeled them as Credence Good markets, where unlike experience goods, the quality and quantity of treatment cannot be verified even post-transaction. Dulleck and Kerschbamer(2006) in their analysis and survey of articles pertaining to such literature point out that price signals fail to transmit information about the parameters and tend to be flat among poor and good experts alike. The Experts can take advantage of the information gap and hence are incentivized to deceive particularly the less sophisticated or naïve buyers.
<div class="page" title="Page 2">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

While Dulleck and Kerschbamer(2006) do suggest that to minimize the probability of being deceived, one has to end up choosing the busiest or an expert who charges a premium, they do not account for that when experts do have a capacity constraint, their incentive for putting less effort per consumer increases. In fact, as has been empirically shown in health markets of developing countries where public hospitals can at most give 3.2 minutes on average per patient (Das et al, 2008).

&nbsp;
<div class="page" title="Page 2">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<blockquote><em><strong>FOOTNOTE - </strong>Language here would be defined as a ‘market language’ – An abstraction which assumes that if the analysis is of a market, then the world is divided into two ontologies, where each ontology would be described by a language. So for the real world which encompasses the Economic world a natural language – English, and for the participants of the market, a language which describes their ontology better than the vague natural language. We will call this language “Oikos”. It is important to note here that “</em>oikos<em>” is a specialized language projected in the natural language. For e.g. The word Equilibrium exists both in real ontology and Economic ontology – but might mean completely different things in each specification.</em></blockquote>
&nbsp;
<div class="page" title="Page 3">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

The first essay proposes to analyze such markets where I assume that all market participants (buyers, sellers, intermediaries) are distributed spatially according to their proficiency in that market’s language. So if L is the market language, the market participants are identified on the basis of their endowment of L in the static game. The experts are assumed to be ‘trained with certification’ and the only way agents can learn the language is by experience. The spatial distribution makes this model one with vertical differentiation, but since the consumers cannot distinguish the seller’s type (given that all sellers speak better than the consumers) or do so probabilistically, this makes this model one of a horizontal distribution in terms of the consumers. The equilibrium of the model will be determined by the hypothesis that less sophisticated consumers are matched with poor experts. In the dynamic model, the language rules are no longer fixed, with mutations on words and grammar, in an evolutionary model. The hypothesis then is whether, over time, a specialized language is meant as a barrier for consumers to counter the experts’ incentives for fraud. The model can be extended from a single dimension of language proficiency to a bilingual environment, making this a two-dimensional problem with added complexity. The roles of intermediaries as those consumers with a ‘working knowledge’ of the language through experience would be pivotal in search efficiency.

<strong>CAN NO KNOWLEDGE BE BETTER THAN SOME KNOWLEDGE IN THE MARKET?</strong>
<blockquote>
<div class="page" title="Page 3">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

Before I started the practice, a mountain was a mountain and a river was a river. When I was deep into the practice, the mountain was no longer a mountain and river was no longer a river. Now that I have mastered the practice, a mountain is a mountain, and a river is a river.

-Buddhist Zen Koan

</div>
</div>
</div></blockquote>
<div class="page" title="Page 3">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<div class="page" title="Page 3">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

This paper applies the classic Whorfian hypothesis of the causal relationship between language and thought which was earlier stated by Wittgenstein aphoristically as “The Limits of my language means the limits of my world” (Wittgenstein – 1922:5.6). This builds on the idea that language doesn’t just express thought, rather constitutes it. This paper formalizes de Saussure’s (1916) conception of the syntagm and the paradigm and concords it with Shannon’s (1948) theory of valence. The intuition is that what differentiates a formal language and a natural language, where the former is projected in terms of the latter is that it is more ‘precise’ in its vocabulary and grammar rules, that is the number of referents a word has is reduced and is usually one. Such a formal language becomes binding on the combinatorial possibilities of words to form sentences, and parallel conception in the ontological space means a ‘narrow outlook’ of the world. This is of course not true for all the experts of that formal language, but for the beginners. For example, a layman is not constrained in the speculations of his observations say in light of the economic crisis (whether he is right or wrong), but for an economics undergraduate who has training in basic economics (colloquially termed Economics 101), would not only try to fix the crisis in the mould of his training, but would rather be confident about it. But for a veteran economic theorist can invent new rules to explain the crisis, guided by experience and knowledge. The formalization of this hypothesis is the object of the second paper.
<div class="page" title="Page 3">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

The formalization of this idea can be applied in varied ways, one of which relates to the previous paper on the market for expert services. The mechanisms of this are that the naïve consumer matching with automatically the busiest expert while the slightly more informed trusts his judgment which within a ‘lemons market’ scenario can prove disastrous. The second mechanism is that in the interaction process with the expert, given that the expert gets the signal to put more effort in forming the interpretable linguistic message but for the intermediate, the expert sends a precise message in the market language which the intermediate might not interpret. This can be formalized using the wisdom and technical definitions in terms of language as mapped out in the first section. In a flexible grammar approach, training does not imply wisdom. So the knowledge of grammar doesn’t mean its usage and a complex signal hence wouldn’t be interpreted in the duration of the interaction.
<blockquote><em><strong>FOOTNOTE -  1. </strong></em>I prefer to use the term ‘rationally ignorant’ or ‘rationally submissive’

2. We can assume technical training provides wisdom although at a fractional increase compared with experience.</blockquote>
<strong>VAGUENESS AND PRECISION</strong>
<div class="page" title="Page 4">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

Economic interactions and transactions are expressed through natural language which as has been established is vague. Lipman (2006) provides an excellent study of whether being vague than precise is ‘monotonically bad’. The answer is obviously no. Depending on context, the interacting agents, and other factors, vague language cannot only precisely transmit information in lesser effort, but can bypass rules to present a simplified approximation of the complex information signal. (For example, metaphors and analogies). However, the simplification of language in sense of Ockham’s razor (Say a popular book on Quantum Physics for the mass market), definitely has strategic considerations, or as Crawford and Sobel propose that partitioning can reveal an informative equilibrium in cheap talk. These issues apply to how language is used, that is concerns Pragmatics. Since each word in a vocabulary ascribes a network of meanings, usually correlated with one another4. With all these points under consideration, and factors such as the costs of precision, strategic considerations and the linguistic model described above, a strategic information transmission of the spirit of Crawford and Sobel(1982) would be studied under natural language interpretation of message states, in what Lipman(2006) conjectured for the ideal bounded rational study of vagueness.

<strong>THE BILINGUAL GAME</strong>
<div class="page" title="Page 4">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

This essay provides a theoretical reasoning of why some natural languages fair better amongst others in terms of the market language. Suppose if L is the language of economic agents, representing concepts in the totality of factual and counterfactuals of its sentences, and two natural languages say English(E) and French(F). The question is whether the two languages can equally project L? These two languages should fulfill some base requirements, that is to describe the ontologies of the real world in the dictionary sense. Once both languages fulfill the criteria, then the hypothesis can be tested. The intuition is that L can then be projected in both E and F, but once the rules and vocabulary are not fixed, the use of the language would mean that L will itself change(mutate) in the long run, where the frequency of use of L in terms of E or F will determine the mutation. Since L is expressed in natural language, new concepts in L would emerge in the natural language of E. So that in the conversation between E and F, the speaker of E would be better able to communicate L, rather than F who would then have to learn E apart from L in terms of F. This paper outlines the social dimension of language and pragmatics. This paper would be in similar lines in the idea to the one by Lang(1986) who uses a transaction costs approach and not an informational one to show how a language can be discriminatory.
Other games and ideas such as the Chinese Whispers game of message distortion over multiple agents transmission, the problem of information cascades and herd behavior and linguistic analysis, and other questions would be considered as avenues for further research.
<blockquote><em><strong>FOOTNOTE - </strong></em>Wittgenstein(1953) called these Family Resemblances</blockquote>
<strong>BIBLIOGRAPHY</strong>
<div class="page" title="Page 5">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

RABIN, M. (1990): “Communication between Rational Agents,” Journal of Economic Theory, 51, 144–170.

FARRELL, J., AND M. RABIN (1996): “Cheap Talk,” Journal of Economic Perspectives, 10, 103–118.

CRAWFORD, V. P., AND J. SOBEL (1982): “Strategic Information Transmission,” Econometrica, 50, 1431–1451.

B. Whorf (1956) Language, Thought and Reality: Selected Writings of Benjamin Lee Whorf (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press).

J. Marschak (1965) ‘Economics of Language’, Behavioral Science, 10, 135–140.

N. Chomsky (1957) Syntactic Structures (The Hague: Mouton).

A. Rubinstein (2000) Economics and Language (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press). Lipman, Barton L. (2006): “Why is Language Vague?” manuscript, Boston University.

Wittgenstein, Ludwig (1922) Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus, Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, London.

Wittgenstein, Ludwig (1953) Philosophical Investigations, Blackwell, Oxford.

</div>
</div>
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

&nbsp;

GRIN, F. (2009). The economics of language: survey, assessment, and

</div>
</div>
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

prospects. International Journal of the Sociology of Language, 121(1), pp. 17-44.

</div>
</div>
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

&nbsp;

Dulleck, Uwe, and Rudolf Kerschbamer. 2006."On Doctors, Mechanics, and Computer Specialists: The Economics of Credence Goods."

</div>
</div>
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

Journal of Economic Literature44(1): 5-42.

</div>
</div>
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">

&nbsp;

Das J (2011) The Quality of Medical Care in Low-Income Countries: From Providers to Markets. PLoS Med 8(4): e1000432.

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
&nbsp;

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>127</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2018-02-17 07:39:27</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2018-02-17 07:39:27</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>a-quixotic-research-proposal-in-economic-theory</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[14833819083]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1518853172]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10213717494704109";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Of Good, Evil and all that Jazz- A Case for Objective Morality by Immanuel Kant</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2018/05/14/of-good-evil-and-all-that-jazz-a-case-for-objective-morality-by-immanuel-kant/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2018 16:48:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=129</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[caption id="attachment_130" align="aligncenter" width="360"]<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-130" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2018/05/kant_360x450.jpg" alt="kant_360x450" width="360" height="450" /> Immanuel Kant to the artist - "Paintshop ya hear me, for the bitches ya meen?"[/caption]

&nbsp;

It has been three months since my previous post. With regards to the content of the previous post, I am glad to reveal that my Ph.D. proposal was modified to be more grounded in mainstream economic theory, but retained the spirit of the exercise and hence left my faculty, my advisory committee and myself, better off. I have since submerged in getting back to intensive reading everything that was not related to my research but finally composed myself to start on my thesis, to be presented in three years from today ideally.

I, however, am glad though the absence from the blogosphere made me guilty, I am back with perhaps the most ambitious post to date, for I have lost my philosophical virginity to Immanuel Kant, the greatest and one of the most difficult philosophers to have existed, and have finished two-thirds of his writings and have made copious notes, and fairly confident of having understood his works somewhat. The present post outlines Kant's ethical theory, from his celebrated '<strong>Groundwork for Principles of the Metaphysics of Morals</strong>'(yeah try saying that 5 times!)

It is important to note that this is a purely theoretical exercise, and even if you agree with the system or not, take it as a piece of art at the least, and something to think about at the most. I have tried to be lucid and precise, however, I yet lack the skills to interpret his work well enough to explain like you're five, and it is going to be a somewhat long post, but I request you to save it or bookmark it, and really stick with it because a) I have spent a lot of time in extracting Kant's thought from a very dense book. b) It would be worthwhile at least as an entry to perhaps without question one of the greatest thinkers to have ever lived. And now, we shall start in our endeavor.

<strong>Disclaimer</strong> - Please don't focus on the use of pronouns as I've used man as the mode of analysis, out of convenience since I have a penis and think like a male.
<h1><strong>Of Good, Evil and all that Jazz- A Case for Objective Morality by Immanuel Kant</strong></h1>
There is a fine distinction between Natural Science and Social Science, for, in the world of natural science, we use our senses to interpret external objects, that is, while we can be sure that there is a tree in front of us, we are limited by the resolution of our eyes to interpret what our brain shows us of the tree. An animal with far stronger eyesight might see a shade of colors unfathomable to us, thereby seeing a truer picture of the reality, but we can’t be sure that anything can grasp the true nature of any object, say, except for a perfect omniscient being, let us call it God.

Social Science, however, is different. Let’s start with the basis of all social science – Ethics. Why? Well, it is the foundation on which the premise of a civilization rests. The acknowledgment of principles of right and wrong is the source of Law and Justice. Politics and Economics derive from the interpretation of right, wrong; pleasure and pain which we derive from? Well - Ethics. It is bad to hurt another person can be within one's conscience, but as a law means doing so would incur punishment formally. Ethics can these days be seen in a more metaphysical light thanks to anticipated developments in the not so distant future.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align:center;"><strong>Suppose you design artificial intelligence and have to program an ethical system for the machine to follow. Would you want it to statistically emulate humans? I hope not. Humans would go extinct in a year. How to then program ethics into an intelligent machine, such that within the scope of a free will, the machines still make choices under the logical system supplanted by us, and which would not get us annihilated?</strong></p>
</blockquote>
Ethics is a construction of human thought(or is it?) Unlike objects which can never be known in their true form because we are limited by sense, we can create an imagined world which has every property carefully laid out by us. To do so, we need to create a theory that is independent of all actual experience(No empirical observations, say when designing that machine.) Can we do that? How do we do that? <strong>Kant did that</strong>. And he did it pretty well. But the result is something that we would probably be underwhelmed with. The generality of theory to make it independent from all facets of how humans actually live makes it somewhat restrictive. But it’s not the result but the accomplishment of the construction of such a system that is important here. And so we start-
<h3><span style="text-decoration:underline;"><strong>THE RECIPE OF OBJECTIVE MORALITY</strong></span></h3>
We start with the first axiom -  <strong>Agency or </strong><strong>Free Will</strong> <em>(Remember this because it’s important in the last section)</em>

Humans can make choices and can deliberately choose to not choose something just because well, they can. Nature has granted humans with two devices to take actions – <strong>Instinct and Reason</strong>. Instinct acts on two principles – Pleasure and Pain. Instinct is like an internal command, which may or may not be reasonable. (<em>In fact, Daniel Kahneman has worked out the various cognitive biases inherent in instinctual actions, what we now call heuristics in modern psychology</em>)

We seek things which provide pleasure and avoid things which cause pain. (<em>This is the starting point of utilitarian theory</em>). However, man can transcend and negate instincts. He can avoid immediate pleasure with a view that abstaining from such pleasure might benefit his health or yield future dividends. This higher faculty is that of <strong>Reason </strong>and is, to a degree, unique to humans. As individual humans are different in their biology, cultures, and dispositions, how do we abstract humanity to a homogeneous whole? Well, Reason. When properly applied, logical reasoning should deduce fixed conclusions from a set of premises.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align:center;"><strong>The Faculty of Reason, in other words, is universal in all Rational Beings.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<strong>Reason</strong> stands above <strong>I</strong><strong>nstinct</strong> since it can validate instinctual actions but not vice versa. The faculty of reason is what separates us from the animal, for instinctual actions occur in both. Just as Science is not necessary for humans to live but can indeed be used as a faculty to make life convenient and better, Reason, similarly, is a powerful faculty for us to make civilization possible.

So to start, we have <strong>Free Will </strong>as an axiom and <strong>Reason </strong>as the optimum faculty to take actions, we can proceed towards an <strong>Ethical Theory.</strong> A theory starts with definitions, and the first and foremost definition we require is that of a  <strong>Good Action</strong>.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align:center;"> Kant defines <em><strong>Good</strong> as <strong>Goodness-in-itself</strong></em>. (Ha! but let me explain)</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="text-align:left;">Though there can be possibly many virtues(intelligence, patience etc.,), they lose their essence when used as means towards some goal. Say donation of wealth to save taxes or raise one's position in society. The <strong>Good Will</strong> is the only source of moral value. But we still haven't defined the <strong>Good Will</strong>, and shall proceed towards that.</p>

<blockquote>
<p style="text-align:center;"><em>Many consider stoic living or frugality to be a virtue, but is it though? Moderation or detachment can be attributes of evil(Michael Corleone comes to mind)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<h3><span style="text-decoration:underline;"><strong>DUTY AS THE "GOOD" WILL</strong></span></h3>
The Human Will exercises judgment through three methods: - <strong>Self Interest, Inclinations, and Duty.</strong> Those who have studied economics can understand it in terms of the utility approach(<em>Kantian ethics are opposed to Utilitarianism- I use it just for easier exposition</em>)

Suppose we take a <strong>good action</strong> – say philanthropy is <strong>good</strong>. For some, what matters is that the deed was done, but not so for Kant.
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align:center;"><em>If an act of charity is done in expectation of recognition or to save taxes, then it is an action borne out of <strong>self-interest</strong>. For Kant, this doesn’t entail moral worth since the person doing the action is deriving value directly out of it.</em></p>
</blockquote>
Suppose that the philanthropic action is done not from <strong>self-interest, </strong>but simply because it makes one happy. For Kant, even such actions don’t entail objective moral worth, since it is done out of an individual's <strong>inclinations or preferences</strong>. An example would drive the argument better:-
<blockquote>Let there be two persons A and B where B derives happiness from donating food, while A does not. Suppose A and B then both perform the philanthropic deed. For the utilitarian, there’s no difference in the actions of A and B, but for Kant, the action was easier for B since he derives happiness from it, the total value of the deed goes to his utility function, and the rest as say moral value. For A instead, who doesn’t derive any happiness from the deed, the value from action doesn't exist as individual utility, but solely as moral value. Thus A has done something more moral than B in performing the same action.</blockquote>
<p style="text-align:center;"><strong><em>Hence, Duty is the sole generator of moral value, for if done by actions of preference or self-interest would not be objective, as preferences vary among people, and then the only outcome to generate objective moral value is not to see the actions as a means to happiness, but rather the action itself, even if it provides discomfort, so that one need not even consider utility concerns when taking certain actions.</em></strong></p>
Here, two clarifications are required:-
<ul>
	<li><em>There might be objections that since Kant started with  Free Will, then isn't a <strong>binding duty</strong> self-contradictory?</em></li>
</ul>
Kant answers that though the will must indeed submit to duty, the will does so <em>willingly </em>i.e. out of respect since the rational will acknowledges that such duty transcends the will so that any rational person can determine the sanctity of a duty through the application of transparent reason.
<ul>
	<li><em>What if the laws and duties represent the self-interest of the legislator?</em></li>
</ul>
The answer to this question is the focus of the next section and introduction of the crux of Kant's system - <strong>The Categorical Imperative.</strong>
<h3><span style="text-decoration:underline;">THE LEGISLATION OF LAWS/DUTIES</span></h3>
It would be prudent to start with a definition.
<blockquote><em>A <strong>M</strong><strong>axim</strong> is any principle an individual might consider to be <strong>good</strong>. Once a maxim passes <strong>Kant’s criterion of legislation</strong> it can hence be enacted as a <strong>L</strong><strong>aw.</strong></em></blockquote>
Take any maxim, say a person believing that <strong>white lies</strong> to be <strong>good</strong>. Can such a maxim be objectively good? Surely not. A way to test it is through the <em><strong>Principle of Universality(Kant's criterion) - </strong></em>
<blockquote>Let's suppose that the maxim of <strong>white lies </strong>is a universal law to which every person is subject. Is it <strong>good? </strong>It would then imply that even the government could lie to its people whose duty then is to "protect people" by lying about policy enactments. But this is a logical contradiction since the only cause to lie would be <strong>as a means</strong> to protect its own interests rather than as <strong>a good-in-itself.</strong></blockquote>
It is hence stated as thus:-
<blockquote><em>Any individual maxim which is <strong>not</strong> a universally applicable as a <strong>law</strong> must contradict itself . </em></blockquote>
When is a maxim then applicable as a law? For Kant, only when it is <strong>categorical.</strong>
<h4><span style="text-decoration:underline;"><strong>THE CATEGORICAL IMPERATIVE and THE KINGDOM OF ENDS</strong></span></h4>
An imperative or a command can either be <strong>Hypothetical(Conditional) </strong>or <strong>Categorical(Unconditional). </strong>

So if the command is – <em><strong>You shall not lie</strong></em>, it is non-contingent, and a universal principle, but however if the command is - <em><strong>You shall not lie for lest it destroy your credibility</strong></em>, the maxim is then conditional. The difference between both is that while the first holds <strong>value in itself</strong>, that is not lying, the second derives <strong>value as a means to something</strong>, that is, credibility. So even if the action is the same, that is not lying, the moral worth of the first is clearly more than the second, and while the first principle is applicable universally and hence objective, the second applies to the subject in question.

Law within a society could arise from divine, sovereign, or through modern democratic sources. The legislator can issue commands for his own self-interest, but if the law is categorical and not hypothetical, two things prevent such a happening.
<ol>
	<li>The legislator himself then must be the object of the law, which prevents him from creating exigencies through which he could create exceptions possible only in the Hypothetical imperative.</li>
	<li>Self-interest can still manifest itself in categorical imperative when universal commands still serve the interests of the legislators. However, the only solution to such a problem is Kant's final solution, stated as follows:-</li>
</ol>
<blockquote> <em><strong>The Universal Law(The Categorical Imperative) can only be realized when Man is viewed as an end-in-himself.</strong></em></blockquote>
What does Kant mean when he says that every rational human is an end in itself? He means that any law which aims at maximization of social welfare cannot use humans as means towards such a goal, because human welfare is exactly the goal of such a law. A ruler using slavery as a means to achieve economic progress contradicts this principle even if the country benefits through rapid development and might increase overall social utility. This is better illustrated in the following example:-

When humans are ends-in-themselves, a person’s utility should come from the increase in utility of the other in the same proportion. That is:-
<blockquote><strong>U(A/[AB]) = U(A/[AA]) = U(B/[BA]) = U(B/[BB]) {Here "/" signifies given or "if" - interpreted as utility to A from an action of A to B should be equal to utility to A when he does an action for himself - Note that this is only applicable for "Duties" or "Laws" and not all actions or moral principles - Moral Laws can be imagined as Fundamental Rights as maxims.) </strong></blockquote>
&nbsp;

<strong>Since the increase(decrease) in A’s utility from an action means the increase(decrease) in B’s utility from the same action, this satisfies Kan’ts criterion as a universal law of nature which is the categorical imperative.</strong> Now when we remove utility from this system such that it is a law bound by duty, which the rational will can ascertain, we are left with pure moral worth maximization. (of course inclinations, in reality, do differ, but when everything is determined by law, inclinations don’t really matter, as they introduce subjectivity into an objective system). The above final proof may seem convoluted but it has remarkably intuitive implications. This sums up Kant's entire moral theory.
<h3></h3>
<blockquote><strong><em>At the most basic level, as pure humans, all humans hold the same intrinsic value, regardless of social status or skills, which can add market value or fancy value over and above the absolute intrinsic value.</em></strong></blockquote>
&nbsp;
<blockquote><em><strong>All rational beings are equal by law. This includes the legislator of laws who must be equally subject to the laws for the system to be consistent.</strong></em></blockquote>
&nbsp;
<h3><span style="text-decoration:underline;">IS ETHICS REAL OR A CONSTRUCT OF OUR BRAINS?</span></h3>
If you remember from the first section, we started with <strong>Free Will</strong> as the only axiom. That is the entire theory is contingent on that axiom through which Kant proceeded with his ethical system. Now Kant prepares us for the <em>Grand Finale</em>.

Kant now shows that if this axiom is a <strong>truth</strong>, the whole system would become real and independent purely constituted from <strong>Reason</strong>. <strong>Free Will</strong> is tautological with the <strong>autonomy of the will. </strong>Kant argues that <strong>Free Will cannot be an assumption which we start with</strong> since it’s a necessary truth. In ignoring the affectations of senses in forming our morality and starting the system from reason itself is an act of free will, through which we uncover the concept of freedom as well.
<blockquote><strong><em>The will doesn’t define freedom but exercises it. Without freedom there is no will. Without a will there is no freedom.</em></strong></blockquote>
The faculty of creating an intelligible world through the application of reason to the will is what Kant terms ‘<strong>Practical Reason</strong>’ as opposed to the faculty of ‘<strong>Pure Reason</strong>’ applied in understanding our external world.
<blockquote><em><strong>Ethics as opposed to Metaphysics of Nature starts with the Subject creating the Object and can hence know its reality in full. Here, in theory, we are Gods and hence understand the objects for we are the ones who have designed it. In nature, the object stands apart from us, We start with the object and attempt to understand it, while in ethics, understanding precedes the object of our exercise.</strong></em></blockquote>
Now that Freedom is real, what causes Freedom of the Will to arise? That is a question best left to the scientists, and not the philosopher since philosophy can only go so far to prove that it exists and is real, but not how it came to be...]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>129</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2018-05-14 16:48:09</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2018-05-14 16:48:09</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>of-good-evil-and-all-that-jazz-a-case-for-objective-morality-by-immanuel-kant</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_old_date</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2018-05-13]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1526316492]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[17841705302]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10214382620611841";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>kant_360x450</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2018/05/14/of-good-evil-and-all-that-jazz-a-case-for-objective-morality-by-immanuel-kant/kant_360x450/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 19:39:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2018/05/kant_360x450.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>130</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2018-05-11 19:39:01</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2018-05-11 19:39:01</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>kant_360x450</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>129</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2018/05/kant_360x450.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2018/05/kant_360x450.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:360;s:6:"height";i:450;s:4:"file";s:88:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2018/05/kant_360x450.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:49732;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>A Natural Calamity</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2018/07/27/a-natural-calamity/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 07:53:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=133</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[I have a tendency of having some really odd dreams, which I never knew how to make sense of, so after a particularly cryptic dream today, I quickly grabbed some pen and paper and jotted a poem out of it, which still doesn't make sense to me, but might do so for you. Our unconscious thoughts are extremely powerful, and we can't take them lightly I feel, So I feel it would do no harm if I just convert the dream to a poem. Do tell what you make of it.

&nbsp;
<h1>A NATURAL CALAMITY</h1>
<p style="text-align:center;"></p>

<blockquote>
<h2 style="text-align:center;"><strong><em>Gazed into the morning sky,
A pulp of Golden Orange Green;

The Giant Ape leapt to the nigh,
Clutching the eagle by its beak;</em></strong><strong><em>

A riot of monkeys erupted surprise,
A fear of strength they scattered through;
For hurled back I into the night,
puzzling at this grave misfortune;

Tethered myself I doth heard,
The Great Fire burnt the forest down;
An ash of golden orange green, they said,
'The sky is dead', O I renounced;

Darted back I to the stream,
A new hope hoped the heart anew;
Alas the ape caged by ape I saw,
Caged the grin of thy insanity;</em></strong></h2>
&nbsp;

&nbsp;

&nbsp;</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>133</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2018-07-27 07:53:35</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2018-07-27 07:53:35</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>a-natural-calamity</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1532678018]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[20443314133]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_external</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:1:{s:8:"facebook";a:1:{i:14597494;s:38:"https://facebook.com/10214890756914931";}}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_done_14703420</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wpas_done_14597494</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>The Suicide of God</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2018/09/24/the-suicide-of-god/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 20:35:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=135</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I - The Day of God</h2>
&nbsp;

T’was a sunny Sunday morning,

The warm light permeated the bones;

The winds made music with trees and when,

The first screams were heard at noon;

&nbsp;

Bodan, the town where God resided,

In heart of every woman, child, and man;

Loved they life, nature, and God as one,

Until God played them with a godly prank;

&nbsp;

The children played, the elder waved,

Beautiful morning for Mass it was;

And did every Bodan sang with heart,

For it was special for them and special for God.

&nbsp;

For God is this and God is that we say,

God exists or God is Man;

God is nature, spirit or cosmos we hail;

Yet that day they didn’t foresee God’s plan;

&nbsp;

The Sun bled red and the sky rumbled,

A locust of brown gas enshrined Bodan;

<em>Mercy!</em> Bodan begged in song,

To no heed their cries availed;

&nbsp;

For God is not human, is he?

Better be not for what we are;

A swift, painless exit and a seat beside him,

Wasn’t it our prayers answered at last?

&nbsp;

And as to the dust, did a stampede add,

As God slowly declared his plans;

Dug their nails to mother’s breast,

As the children did,

<strong>Fade to Black.</strong>

&nbsp;

<em>Life is Suffering, my children you doth know,</em>

<em>And a gift of my existence did I bestow!</em>

<em>But thy sins though forgiven, forbid me,</em>

<em>From giving thee a place with thy progeny,</em>

<em>In the eternal truth of heaven;</em>

&nbsp;

<em>‘I hath hit two birds with one stone’, rejoiced God,</em>

<em>Nay three, with the innocent in heaven;</em>

<em>And to let them be known of their father as well,</em>

<em>To test their faith through this ingenious method.</em>

And so did God command the children’s souls to Heaven.

&nbsp;
<h2>II – The Return of Man or lack thereof</h2>
&nbsp;

The brownness thus disappeared, no trace but a golden hue,

Clean as cleanliness could be, godliness was there they now knew;

The children’s pale faces did smile, in a body but devoid of any life;

‘<em>Wake up</em>!’ gently sang the mothers, yet not a single voice could come through;

&nbsp;

As the tears rolled by and throats went dry, it suddenly dawned anew,

It was but God’s gift, his mercy, his plan, his to take and his to provide;

God and man’s wrath did know no bounds, until did they see a grieving mother;

For then did men see, that murder, crimes of flesh, is but petty,

That true blackness, of something even God might fear, lies in a mother’s eyes beside her dead.

&nbsp;

And the men finally realized that God’s joke was so clear,

<em>Have we not bowed at nature’s wrath?</em>

<em>But only standing afar did we,</em>

<em>That God’s jokes hath made us laugh;</em>

<em>But now that the honor of being audience to the joke was ours,</em>

<em>The only laughter we heareth is silence;</em>
<h2> III – The Song of God</h2>
&nbsp;

The silence slowly broke in voices,

First one and two then three and four;

Till the wailing reached God’s own ears,

<em>‘Whether the subject or object am I?’</em> did he wonder

<em>Their imperfect language doesn’t make it clear!</em>;

&nbsp;

The betrayal by God was the message he didn’t hear,

Or did he but he didn’t care?

Because the women did unite hand in hand now,

In one final song of reverence.

&nbsp;

As the innocent bodies were picked up and cremated,

The men to fulfill God’s unusual wishes,

<em>Is there a reason? Should we fear, love, hate that one,</em>

<em>Can we ever question him?</em> They couldn’t ask.

&nbsp;

But no such question arose in the mothers’ hearts,

Now they were resolute, their child to them is more than a god,

This our creator did not assume.

The eerie beautiful summer Sunday, clear now from the brown gas,

Now covered in black the sky was the smoke of the children’s ash.

&nbsp;
<h2> IV - Redemption</h2>
&nbsp;

The Song was a passion of God’s suffering, with the intensity of antiquity,

What was not antique being a new technique, The song of the ritual sacrifice;

‘<em>Oh, A song for their blessed children!</em>’, God said of this new development,

Yet God knows all but he didn’t know thus, for he was the song’s tribute.

&nbsp;

There grew a sinister strength, as the women and men united in song,

They mocked God now, naughty children of their father;

For the punishment for the deed they had already accrued,

The mocking song grew louder in cruel laughter,

Crying or laughing or both together? And thus God now got the inkling,

Of something to come now, ‘<em>The Horror!</em>’ said he, quivering.

&nbsp;

The defiance in prayer now stood at contrast, with laughing

God thundered, ‘<em>How dare they</em>?’,

But eyes wide open, they stared into his heart,

‘<em>Fools! Don’t they know their place?’</em>;

&nbsp;

Now the Funeral song started,

<em>‘Oh! The blasphemy! The Murder of God they intend!’</em>;

<em>‘Burn this holy ground with their skins would they!’</em>

<em>‘Teach them burning I shall for eternity!’</em>

&nbsp;

The song now in its final stages stretched,

Hesitancy, struggle, but no stoppage yet;

The struggle made the beauty sublime,

A beautiful song of the dead;

&nbsp;

As the breath and heart lose their timber,

As tapered the final stretch;

Slower and slower and slower still,

When God found out the game thus planned;

&nbsp;

<em>Does God have Free Will?</em> We ask,

<em>‘Then why is the world the way it is?’</em>

<em>Do the choices he maketh the world better,</em>

<em>How possible if the world starts in perfect?</em>

&nbsp;

The answer now we know as did they,

They, who forced God to play his hand;

Man’s Will overpowered him, and joined the song did he,

Of the folly of his actions, for his own children did not know he.

&nbsp;

&nbsp;

God can never lose, this fact is absolute.

But in winning this game he lost to Mankind

As they slowly fell to victory, and as the song petered out at last,

Collapsed they did, enveloped by whiteness;

<strong>Fade to White.</strong>

&nbsp;
<h2 style="text-align:justify;">PostScript</h2>
&nbsp;

In heaven find their children and play, in fields of pearly heavenly white,

Yet God came and smiled as they smiled, below an empty church stood still;

No one to pray and no one to sing, such an emptiness was this,

But God is true emptiness and emptiness is God, is the sage wisdom, and with this,

God committed suicide and played with his children.

&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>135</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2018-09-24 20:35:53</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2018-09-24 20:35:53</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>the-suicide-of-god</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1537821357]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[22493275264]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>How to make a damn near perfect cup of coffee</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=137</link>
		<pubDate></pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=137</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[I love coffee. This statement would have much more strength to it if it wasn't so generic and easy to say. I mean I really love coffee, to say that I owe my sanity and any if at all productivity to it. But it's not just a source of caffeine, it is a warm cup of hugs and cuddles and tastes fucking fantastic.

Yet not all cups of coffee are created equal. To truly appreciate this gift to mankind, one needs to ditch the barbaric practice of shoving instant coffee powder into hot water and then saying "tea is better". No. It's unforgivable. You don't belong to a civilization, you cave dweller. On the other extreme, being a pretentious prick of a coffee connoisseur who can't taste coffee if it is not at 72 degrees and the crockery gives way to lab equipment, well, you need to get a life. You see, like all good things, the investment to return ratio in making a good cup of coffee follows diminishing returns, so even slight changes to the instant crap we drink can produce a 50 percent jump. That's why in modesty I claim a near perfect cup, the mythical ideal only exists in our mind. And so we begin...

<strong>STEP 1 - Get some Goddamn Coffee Beans, you lazy toad. Preferably Arabica.</strong>

&nbsp;

[gallery ids="138,139" type="square" columns="2" link="none"]

&nbsp;

[gallery ids="139,138" type="rectangular" link="none"]

If you want to taste the subtle flavours, say some imported Ethiopian beans, then get a light roast. The roasting process makes the beans oily and darker, and ends in a a bolder, bitter aftertaste. One can get decent beans from Indian Coffee Board in CP, Delhi, or I highly recommend Devans in Jor Bagh which has been my go to place for years now, at about 400 Rs for 500 gram worth of beans.

&nbsp;

<strong>Step 2 - Grinding of Beans</strong>

&nbsp;

[gallery ids="140,141" type="columns"]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>137</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-05-27 18:25:29</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>draft</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>img20190527102234</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/img20190527102234/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 10:24:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102234.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Using Dark Roast, HIgh Strength Indian Peaberry]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>138</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-05-27 10:24:03</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-05-27 10:24:03</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>img20190527102234</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102234.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102234.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:3072;s:6:"height";i:4096;s:4:"file";s:93:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102234.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:1250183;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_image_alt</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>img20190527102417</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/img20190527102417/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 10:24:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102417.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The aroma of a freshly opened pack is divine]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>139</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-05-27 10:24:06</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-05-27 10:24:06</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>img20190527102417</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102417.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102417.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:3072;s:6:"height";i:4096;s:4:"file";s:93:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102417.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:799786;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_image_alt</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>img20190527102312</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/img20190527102312/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 11:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102312.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>140</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-05-27 11:12:17</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-05-27 11:12:17</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>img20190527102312</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102312.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102312.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:3072;s:6:"height";i:4096;s:4:"file";s:93:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102312.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:827012;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>img20190527102509</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/img20190527102509/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 11:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102509.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>141</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-05-27 11:12:19</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-05-27 11:12:19</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>img20190527102509</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102509.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102509.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:3072;s:6:"height";i:4096;s:4:"file";s:93:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102509.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:634825;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>img20190527102234-1</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/img20190527102234-1/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 11:14:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102234-1.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>142</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-05-27 11:14:03</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-05-27 11:14:03</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>img20190527102234-1</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102234-1.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102234-1.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:3072;s:6:"height";i:4096;s:4:"file";s:95:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102234-1.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:1250183;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>img20190527102417-1</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/img20190527102417-1/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 11:14:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102417-1.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>143</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-05-27 11:14:06</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-05-27 11:14:06</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>img20190527102417-1</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/05/img20190527102417-1.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102417-1.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:3072;s:6:"height";i:4096;s:4:"file";s:95:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/05/img20190527102417-1.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:799786;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>man-on-top-of-mountain</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2019/06/24/an-excerpt-from-friedrich-nietzsches-thus-spake-zarathustra/man-on-top-of-mountain/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 14:04:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/man-on-top-of-mountain.jpg</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>145</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-06-24 14:04:27</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-06-24 14:04:27</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>closed</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>man-on-top-of-mountain</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>inherit</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>144</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>attachment</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<wp:attachment_url>https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/man-on-top-of-mountain.jpg</wp:attachment_url>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attached_file</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/06/man-on-top-of-mountain.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_wp_attachment_metadata</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[a:6:{s:5:"width";i:5472;s:6:"height";i:3648;s:4:"file";s:98:"/home/wpcom/public_html/wp-content/blogs.dir/540/91047136/files/2019/06/man-on-top-of-mountain.jpg";s:5:"sizes";a:0:{}s:10:"image_meta";a:12:{s:8:"aperture";s:1:"0";s:6:"credit";s:0:"";s:6:"camera";s:0:"";s:7:"caption";s:0:"";s:17:"created_timestamp";s:1:"0";s:9:"copyright";s:0:"";s:12:"focal_length";s:1:"0";s:3:"iso";s:1:"0";s:13:"shutter_speed";s:1:"0";s:5:"title";s:0:"";s:11:"orientation";s:1:"0";s:8:"keywords";a:0:{}}s:8:"filesize";i:2633581;}]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>An Excerpt from Friedrich Nietzsche&#039;s &#039;Thus Spake Zarathustra&#039;</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2019/06/24/an-excerpt-from-friedrich-nietzsches-thus-spake-zarathustra/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 14:06:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=144</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>Disclaimer – The following Excerpt has been taken from Friedrich Nietzsche’s sublime magnum opus. The original work is in German, translated into English by Walter Kauffman. Since this book is poetic and rhetoric, translation becomes an important matter. What I present here is my version of this excerpt, with which I have taken full liberties in omitting, editing and even adding a few words, to a version which contains the most spirit for me. The Excerpt is taken from the essay - 'Of Reading and Writing'.</blockquote>
<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-145" src="https://boundedlyirrational.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/man-on-top-of-mountain.jpg" alt="man-on-top-of-mountain" width="5472" height="3648" />

&nbsp;
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>Of all writings, I love only that written in Blood.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>One can't comprehend blood which is unfamiliar, you, the idle reader. </strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>For to know the reader you write for, stinks thy spirit. That in the long run, everyone will learn to read shall ruin writing, nay, but thinking.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>I don't write to be read, I write to be felt. For what I give in blood, shall be understood in blood.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>In the Mountains, the shortest route is between peaks, but then, you must have long legs.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>The mountain air is cold and thin, danger lurks each moment, yet courage laughs.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>The clouds are black under me, and hence I laugh.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>For only those who can laugh can climb the highest. Laugh at what's real, and what's not.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>And the warrior shall reach the top, for wisdom is a woman, favors the best of men.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>"Life is hard to bear" - But if it weren't, would pride exist? Could one enjoy sleep?</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>"Life is hard to bear" - Says the tender finery in Sheep, tis finer to be the noble ass.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>Are we rosebuds? which drop from drops of dew?</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>Do we love life, because we love living? Or because we love loving?</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>Love is madness, and there's a method in madness.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>Life is not a song of butterflies and soap-bubbles for which it's loved.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>There exists a devil, much like your God- Serious, solemn and profound. It is Gravity.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>And my god is your devil, for my god knows how to laugh, and how to dance.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>For one does not kill the devil from anger, but with laughter- Come, warrior, Slay the devil with me!</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>I learned to walk, now I run. Come, let's learn to fly.</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><em><strong>Only when I fly could I see myself under myself, and a god dancing within me. </strong></em></p>
&nbsp;
<p style="text-align:justify;padding-left:60px;"><strong>Thus Spake Zarathustra</strong></p>
&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>144</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-06-24 14:06:49</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-06-24 14:06:49</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>an-excerpt-from-friedrich-nietzsches-thus-spake-zarathustra</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1561385212]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[32144967628]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Dreams</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2019/07/11/dreams/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 08:36:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=150</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[I don't know what it is with me when there are days I can't think of a single word to communicate, to days like today, when I churn out a poem in minutes! Anyway, this one is hazy, I don't think I intended to express a specific meaning, though what came out is instantaneously meaningful to me- hope it arises some strange thoughts in you too which I can't express without playing with words.

Enjoy!
<blockquote>
<p style="text-align:center;">1
Echoes of laughter delayed,
Spraying in this saccharine dismay;
Beasts adorning manly suits,
Sniffed off me the stench of truth;
Enveloping walls suffocate me,
In salty breeze and cold despair,</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">O, God of Heat and Light!</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">seeing thee with thine own eyes,  <span style="color:var(--color-text);">Eternal One!</span></p>
<p style="text-align:center;">This sublime dull yellow,
Richer than rainbows infinite,
The world in its yellowness,
Alarm, beauty and resting peace.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">2
Suddenly opened eyes to a field yellow,
‘Was I dreaming’ asking the nearby fellow;
‘Neither that nor this’ - This is reality,
said he who resembled myself to me.
Feel I’ve wandered here for ages,
Though born today I was,
Familiar faceless smiles around me, I stand
Feet on ground like an oak tree proud,
It was then that time stopped still,
A superman arose among men, two legs less than them.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">3
Flowers giveth and taketh from the bee,
busy in its buzzing work,
Why am I just still? Labour and behold,
Killed bees a dozen three, honey of my labor!
That’s the meaning my fellow dreamers
This, I do not conceal.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">4
Running far across the field,
Bumped to a merry seed, For he,
then praised me for my sleep, 'Nay!'
Said I, 'tis just a dream!' Smiling, he cried</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">Neither slept I
Neither dreamt I, neither awaketh I
Who are you? I asked</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">'Neither I, Am I' - vanished
I farewelled my teacher with a bow.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">5</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">Boring ants! Shifted my gaze,
To the stars above in infinite haze,
Paintings of empty darkness, the void
Reminded me of my blissful sleep,
Prior to this vulgar shattering of a dream,
The real heavens where birds fly,
Is one where I am the sky.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">6
Legs don’t fit a disobedient mind,
Always running after nature’s cry,
Squirrels, Sparrows, Tree and Yarrows,
What is an hour, a year, days a hundred to them?
Today they experienced me for minutes a few,
Only if what minutes were they knew,
Strange creatures, some of us have work to do!</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">7
Napping in this blissful shade,
chided was I, to learn the work and ways,
‘Working now, Hush!’, I said,
Will play games tomorrow my friend,
Bowing, I went back to work.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">8.
As I  saw the children running,
My tired legs, and the sun setting,
My heart yearning I realized,
That I am but the eternal child,
As my weary legs stood again in two,
The sun blazed as a Sunday Noon,
The Child ran with the children,
They laughed - who? Immature children!
Calling themselves adults knowing nature true,
Blind to little gods eternal.</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">9
Lovers embrace, This and I,
As I depart, as we do</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">when spring turns to fall,
Yet I say farewell not with a heavy heart,</p>
<p style="text-align:center;">You see
I am not going either too long or far,
Will see you again a thousand years,
And for a thousand lives, I’ll have to suffer thee.
Till then, let this be heard in tune-
I’ll be right here, just without me and you.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>150</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2019-07-11 08:36:04</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2019-07-11 08:36:04</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>dreams</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1562834167]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[32721434460]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Anxiety- To party or not to party?</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2020/03/20/anxiety-to-party-or-not-to-party/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 21:55:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=152</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Does all anxiety inevitably lead to that one fundamental anxiety, the <em>sine qua non</em> underlying all but never disclosing itself? I am talking of <strong>existential anxiety</strong>, and although not all of us are fixated by philosophical idling in our ever shortening days, not one amongst us can escape it, implicitly if not explicitly.

What if its itself the grappling with fundamental existential questions which makes us shudder, the Unconscious weaving excuses as to avoid facing it head on; that meeting on Wednesday, those supplies to buy, the next movie to watch on Netflix; There is always a task waiting to be checked off, yet one cannot imagine the horror of checking off the last box, and stopping there, no new task, just you.

We are not living in Reality. Of course, this is no Matrix mumbo-jumbo of extreme idealism of existence being an illusion, but rather, our reality does not coincide with <b>**The Reality*</b>*, and here I’m not even talking about the biological constraints that filter the objective world for us[^That’s another matter, for another essay] but psychologically, taking the phenomenal world in front of us as objective. We can’t anyways though, for as a species we have things to do, and to keep doing them - eating, working, romancing, marrying, shopping etc. None of these can be done if we instead just gauged on the bright colours of flowers as facts of naked existence, we make fun of potheads doing so
<blockquote>“Look bro! These flowers shine so radiantly, How come we’ve never looked at them?”</blockquote>
And that I feel, is the problem. We have gone too far, where pausing for a moment, taking a step back, and spending an entire afternoon at the park causes feelings of restlessness in just picturing it. There is so much to do. Yet, ironically, Exactly the picture of watching a flower, and I mean really watching it, like a blind person watching colour for the first time ever, is what all the poets, mystics, and even us, romanticise of, the only consolation we provide - *<i>Someday, certainly not now, there are bills to be paid*.</i>

We have replaced **<b>Reality</b>** with **<b>concepts</b>**, which is faster, efficient, but sacrificial. A tree out there in its naked existence is not a fact of experience with its stimuli, but rather the word, the common noun, the mental picture - “a tree”. This fact, of replacing the child-like perception of trees for concepts of trees, I assert, is the fundamental basis for the inevitable existential crisis in each of our lives. Why inevitable? Because of the one fact - I, and you, and everyone you know, on one day, will die.

This fact of our inevitable mortality, is perhaps the fundamental core of our lives. An empty word, *<b>death</b>* perhaps in one’s youth, of course we are not dying now, and we just take it as fact, like we just take the fact of our existence, like poverty, exists, and we might be subject to, but in some other reality perhaps, and hence escape the question. But that one day comes, if not dead by accident, that we have to go through the painful process of looking our own mortality in its actual impending reality, perhaps being diagnosed with terminal illness, or during old age, we have to make our peace with it.

But before any peace is made, yet grappling with the full reality of it, is pure anxiety. Just ask this question, “<i>what have I really done till now?”</i> And we are on track towards it, yet this approach will never lead to a forceful peace even, content peace is not even a question, for then one must engage with this reality throughout their lives, to keep it in their heart, everyday, like a splinter attached to one’s body leaving one in constant pain, far worse than forgetting oneself in life, which in contrast seems idyllic, and would be so too, if not for the fact that we need be aware the party is about to end. I like this analogy a lot. So the rest of the essay takes from this analogy.
<blockquote>&gt; There is a Party, and we find ourselves in the Party among many others. The Party will end by morning. All of us know that the Party will end, yet some would realise that just some minutes before it actually ends, while others would always have a look on their watch to see how much time is left. In a Party, we party. Now when we party authentically, we lose the sense of time altogether, and we know that too. How does the Party follow for the various party-goers?</blockquote>
The time is finite. You can do a lot in this Party, but if you just keep thinking of how you can party best and remain indecisive, you have had a miserable Party, and want to extend it. Some of us do party, but it’s not an authentic party, for every moment of partying is accompanied by the awareness it will end, and so you try to do everything you can, and have a miserable party. Now let me discuss two more cases. What about that person, who doesn’t care about the time, says “<i>fuck that</i>”, and loses oneself in the party completely. For many, it is the ideal. The best party ever, you have never partied like this before, until the announcement is made, 20 minutes to wrap up. You feel this high, and now don’t want the party to stop, although for different reasons from the first one. Yet you lost all track of time while partying, and now have to come to terms with it. More so, this was your last Party before exams. However, you were so busy enjoying the Party, that you didn’t take time to think “<i>Wow! I’m partying like crazy, and this Party is awesome”</i> when it was at its peak.

There is no escaping the party anxiety because, as self-conscious beings, there is an inescapable need for us to weave experiences of life into a narrative or a story, although its false continuity stems from discrete important events chained together into a coherent story of your life. Without this model of reality, how can we fit experiences? We can live in naked experience, and it is the best if we can, with the caveat then if we don’t delay the inevitable of suddenly waking up from the dream, to know that now it’s time to go to school. But if we did think “<i>wow, this Party is so good</i>” then you have already escaped from authentic experience where the Party and to party have become concepts which has negated at least some part of the actual Reality of the Party and your partying a few moments back. And the tragedy all too real is this - Once you have had thought this thought, you have to now party at this level for the rest of this Party, never fully involved, with some aspect of time always there, infected you like a virus so that in no way can you expect to party like the way you did for the remainder. And then it goes downhill.

As partying beings, who once partied in full authenticity that we were THE PARTY itself, and were by default lost, this rude sudden jolt is the first initiation for many of us into this phenomenon of anxiety, mostly in our early adulthood. We see others partying, some like us who sooner or later had this jolt, suddenly started noticing the Party and the partying people, and asking questions for the first time - as if a new lens had be placed on your head when everything familiar suddenly was not, and the later you woke up, the ruder the jolt. I like to think of it this way -
<blockquote>&gt; You live in your room and don’t pay much attention to it when living there for years. The fan, the cupboards, the floor - all just a fuzzy background. But one day, you find your room completely reorganised, the bed’s orientation reversed, the cupboard shifted, and a new fan. Or perhaps when you visit your bedroom after months of living in the hostel, the first few moments of how alien this all too familiar room, that feeling is the first foray of the rude awakening.</blockquote>
This brings me to that final way of partying, which although the second-best, yet the only practical option for a Party which inevitably ends.(the authentic losing-one-self in the infinite Party being the theoretical best)

This is after that jolt, which is a necessary medicine, to realise the nature of the Party is essentially what the Buddha taught through his Four-Noble-Truths and his Eightfold Path. Where now it’s time to apply the Eightfold path. How to minimise the pain now that you know that you can never party the same way again? Historically, many antidotes have been given- broadly under two schools of thought.
<ul>
	<li>To reject partying, and the Party altogether, so as it doesn’t even matter when it ends.</li>
	<li>To party as hard as possible, with the maxim “<i>Fake it till you Make it”</i>.</li>
</ul>
The Eastern Party Association would tell you this -
<blockquote>&gt; Why are you bothered? You are not a party-man. This Party will end, but there will be many other Parties, even if you don’t remember this one because you got so drunk. Also, all this Party is an illusion, the Real World is WHERE the Party is taking place( even though you have never seen anything outside the Party) , because this Party is YOUR notion of Everything. After the Party ends, you will for the first time see how Insignificant the Party is, for There is something known as the World and that’s the biggest Party. In fact the better you do there, the grander and elite would the Parties you’ll land up in. How do I know this? because If there is a Party, there is something as not-a-Party(since Party ends), and where both Party and non Party happen should be in one place? No? So just see yourself not as the party-goer, not even this Party, but the biggest Party of it all, And sonnyboy, you ARE that Party, It is in you, through you, outside you. It is all there is.</blockquote>
And this new jolt of awareness? And that it will end? and that you can’t lose yourself?
<blockquote>&gt; Why are you taking it as a splinter full of pain? Haven’t you seen that unlike others, you have seen and questioned yourself partying? Now you know what is a genuine fact. This Party will end. And why does one NEED to party in the Party? If you’re in the Party, you are partying, as much as anyone else. Now that you have questioned and sought me, and we are having this conversation, isn’t this Party more than mere dancing and singing? Don’t you feel lighter, of a burden you had always carried but couldn’t give a name? Haven’t you lost yourself in this conversation? Aren’t you looking at this Party with a deeper appreciation for what you took for granted? Unlike that fellow who’s looking at his watch, doing nothing but wanting to party, aren’t you at peace, for now you know you are partying, and that to party is to not only dance, but the fact that you are here, in this Party. This moment, is all you need, all such moments then are enough, there is no chain. The end of the Party is the default mode of Life, you just don’t know that, this is but a mere moment, You don’t remember because you were piss drunk at the last Party and blacked out. And suddenly you woke up thrown into this Party, but now that you are in peace, you don’t need to get piss-drunk anymore, you’re free. So come, lets drink some beer and play Darts, I’ll beat you.</blockquote>
&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>152</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2020-03-20 21:55:16</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2020-03-20 21:55:16</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>anxiety-to-party-or-not-to-party</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[42027161761]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1584741319]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>If Spring comes, can Autumn be far behind?</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2020/04/03/if-spring-comes-can-autumn-be-far-behind/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2020 11:47:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=165</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[We are all in a way, Romanticists, and as much dispassion, disinterestedness, and stoic reservation we muster, we cannot divorce thoughts and concepts with feelings. They can be either feelings of transcendence which cannot be specified into any category, or of distinct colours which we intertwine events with. Perhaps no example is as fundamental as the seasons most of us encounter every year.
<pre> Spring, Summer, Autumn, Winter</pre>
Universally Spring is associated with life, growth, happiness, virility. Summer associated with ripening and peakedness, a maturity, with activity. Autumn is the contrary of spring, associated with preparation of winter, a decay, the waning of life, and finally, winter is associated with harshness, death and anti-life, the contrary of summer.

But we are too much of reductionists, for there is more than meets the eye. We somehow want to believe that Nature behaves with some kind of human exceptionalism, but that is what we attribute to it, and not it to us.

Imagine a lush garden with booming flowers, the archetypal image of spring. Within the lush green grass, Nature goes on as usual, perhaps laughing at our childish desire for it to succumb to our imagery. There is one maxim with which Nature works, and it is this
<pre>Life feeds on itself.</pre>
And for spring to be possible, a transaction must be made, and on magnification, the leaves have all sorts of muck, with flytraps catching up on insects, and ants decomposing dead caracasses.

Only when survival is not at hand does Nature seem beautiful and motherly, in more primal times, Nature was the all mighty God, and not a loving one at that. It needed to be made happy so as to bless us with rains, provide us seasons without plagues, pests or locusts, and more often that not, it demanded a sacrifice of us. And that is what was Nature as such, not an aesthetic beauty or an abstract concept, but the sheer Reality-Sublime because our fates were wholly dependent upon its moods. It thus shaped our character, for the character in this primal stage can be shaped by only one fact - <strong>Survival</strong>
<h2>The Paradox of the Innocent Violent Primitive Man, and the Cunning Cultured Modern Person : Spring in Autumn, Autumn in Spring.</h2>
<h3>Stage I - The Dawn</h3>
As much as we can make cartoons of the primitive man, of a Fred Flinstone, with their cartoonish ape like behavior, Encountering a stranger human of those times would probably get you killed instantly, no questions asked. But this kind of evil is not what we associate with the kinds we are now accustomed to, of the Hitlers and Stalins of the world, but an innocence in this evil, just like a predator is not evil when it hunts or scavenges its prey, and is as innocent as all are in nature, this violence in the primal man rather stems from confusion and fear.

Superstitions can cause evil and violence with the best of intentions, and any modern ethical civilization would necessarily have roots in acts of barbarism which are not from cunning, but only natural. This spring corresponds to then the beginning of human civilization, barbarous from our lens, but in reality the most innocent of all stages, closest to our animal brethren, guided by ritual sacrifices as offerings to God.
<h3>Stage II: The Noon</h3>
The next stage of human civilization again represents a new kind of spring, a more mature one. Though the evolution of culture via agriculture and rise of towns reduce this primordial dependance on mother earth, in this nascent stage, we are still as helpless to the vagaries of nature. The essence of that primal man though doesn't go away, the rituals and witches of the earlier times are simply replaced by priests and organized violence via warfare. Even the scale of victims from violence then increases with a certain indifference towards the reality of it. Violence in warfare is now abstracted into concepts of glory, and innocence is maintained under the veneer of civilization.
<h3>Stage III: Dusk</h3>
The next stage of human spring is of maturation of culture and industry. In fact, in this pre-pubescant industry, war leads the economy, the growth to which we have attributed to this age is a <em>spring of suffering</em>. We tend to casually ignore the fact that economic growth and development historically has been stimulated through warfare, even in our current age that being the case, yet we ignore the fact to not confront the reality of human decadence, for we are now much more moral than the primitive and medieval people surely, as the zeitgeist would like you to believe.

The spring of the age of mass warfare, peace is established with blood. The workers now have overlords, and spring becomes a tradition to celebrate, not a blossoming of the fruits of nature, rather the idea of it,  enjoyed now as a festival in urban centres, divorced of the earlier, rural modes of life. Wars are now normalised and a fact of indifference, which leads to a detached ignorance towards grossly significant acts like mass-murder, now at most being a cause for a shock and awe, of course if it is heinous enough to catch our attention spans. The collective consciousness is now twisted enough, that the destruction of warfare is abstracted and glorified. The connection with the primal man is now severed, the age of innocence is gone, but spring remains, in an artificial construct of civilization.

Still, there was a reason to be upbeat with the onset of spring, despite the corruptions, the stage though goes lower, when this corruption makes the man realize some of it, and is not upbeat anymore. This is the start of spring in the modern era, an <strong>age of nihilism</strong>.
<h3><strong>Stage IV: The Night</strong></h3>
The government is now our overlords, ruling via direct oppression and collection of taxes which only goes into funding wars we don’t need. The farmers, artisans in the countryside are still in touch with the primal man, and hence there are still remnants of that primal innocence, but it is far away from the social consciousness of the times, as exhibited by the major centers of growth i.e. the cities. Still, even the farmers and artisans are not completely immune, for their innocence is now being replaced from joy to one of a prideful glory,  via the medium of money. For money increases power, and power is glory. War in this age is almost farcicial now, a mockery of what it once was, though as much as real, with a scale of destruction hitherto unimagined. It's farcicial because there is no objective which legitimizes it, but abstract ideas which are of no relevance to anyone. The threshold of indifference is so high, that only crimes against the core human principles, of the scale of the holocaust or nuclear weapons invoke the same reactions it did earlier when villages were burnt or massacred, still for some the latter is more barbaric than the former. We are by now, at this stage, tired of this. How much more corruption can there be? Life becomes faster, the economy larger, and it ultimately leads to a revolt, and inevitably to the age of revolution.

Now there's peace, the overlords have been done away with, and after a brief revival of innocence of that earlier spring, there is an eerie lull. For this silence is unnatural, being  seized upon by force, result of which there is a new equilibrium. Revolution leads to further revolutions. The revolutionary of the day past are the present incumbents, who have to now deal with the incoming revolts within discreet circles underground, Now the enemies of the state and its people, in a cruel taste of circularity. This spring is ironic, no? There are mild eruptions, but nothing significant, the new overlords are well trained in this battle art. One could say the continual revolutions carry the primal innocence of destruction which has been our nature And that's why no era can do away with these, the young embedded with the genes of disorder, how are they to blame? The only difference is that rituals are not the rationalizations, but is now called justice. There are now moderates and extremists in every such discreet groups, who differ on the level of acceptable blood during play, and always try to undermine each other, allowing the Stalins of the world to keep afloat.
<h3>Stage V: The Twilight</h3>
The next spring arrives, and with it some necessary optimism, but where lies the joy, and the beauty? The fields are now no longer dependent on nature, Science has mastered it, and won. There is plenty, and still, despite all conveniences of technology, one fact remains constant and will always do so, for we can’t push away the source of philosophical problems inherent in this struggle of Man vs Nature. Any scientific conveniences  of life cannot be filled with the void of that single fact, that Life indeed is, and always be, an endeavour of suffering, and all desires can only strengthen our bondage to it. All remedies, positive experiences would only fail, the new ethics, the abstract concepts, the straightening of nature curves is counter current, and we still wonder why are we still sad, despite our security, our culture?

The decay, does it stem from trading off human nature, the innocent primality for peace and long lives? and when we are devoid of innocence in the age of extreme civilization, is how we return to the roots after all, through an orgy of carnage when bereft of innocence. Killing now is no longer an extreme reaction of revenge, and there is no pity. There is a zeal in it, almost like an explosion of those repressed urges since the first spring, this is spring in full blossom, the blood waters the soil for the renewing of the cycle. Even murder reflects nihilism, the threshold is now at the atomic level, nothing short of nuclear disasters can unite people. In this dionysian bloodbath, the cycle is completed, and the first spring of the next cycle carries on like the beginning. The answer of stopping this cycle is only through what the sages and the critics have prescribed -
<pre>Embrace that primal nature within the civilization.</pre>
One message, different translations ; Two thinkers and a sage that come to mind.

Nietzsche
<pre>The completeness of the Dionysian with Apollo</pre>
Jung
<pre>Embrace thy Shadow.</pre>
Lao Tse
<pre>The Dao that can be traversed is not the Eternal Dao.</pre>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>165</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2020-04-03 11:47:16</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2020-04-03 11:47:16</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>if-spring-comes-can-autumn-be-far-behind</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>1</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_published</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_rest_api_client_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[-1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[42573286470]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1585914439]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Experiencing Time - Some excerpts from Thomas Mann’s The Magic Mountain</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/2020/05/30/experiencing-time-some-excerpts-from-thomas-manns-the-magic-mountain/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 15:47:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=174</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- wp:heading {"level":1} -->
<h1></h1>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Living in the times of a pandemic is no longer a phase we have to simply wait over, rather, as we become accustomed to the circumstances prevailing, we’re now moving towards an <em>equilibrium</em> where such living becomes embedded in our psyche permanently, and consequently, becomes a permanent way of life.(Though surely, we are still in the infant stages of such a maturation and the future is ever uncertain.)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In these state of affairs, an experiment of nature on us one might conceive, we can approach this discontinuity as a tool for a more abstract unity, of what remains unchanged in our mode of living, which are in the domain of philosophical speculation. Indeed, these events make philosophical abstraction easier with empirical validity, and the philosophical concept of interest, of which there has been a definite empirical discontinuity, but at the same time within the chain of the broader philosophical continuity is the <strong>Concept of experiencing time.</strong></p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Like most of us, the initial stages of <em>pandemic living</em> threw me off-balance, and in response I sought some refuge in escapist fictional literature; particularly <em>Thomas Mann’s - The Magic Mountain</em>, which had been glaring at me from the bookshelf for two years.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>I deem even a brief plot summary to be irrelevant in the scope of this essay, for what I am to discuss deals with a few excerpts from the book discussing the notion of <em>Time</em> and <em>Duration</em>, which provoked my fascination in both applying the Philosophy of <em>Henri Bergson</em>(fn); and being relevant to the state of affairs we have found ourselves in.(fn). </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2>From §3 -<em>Mental Gymnastic</em></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:html -->
<blockquote><p>The protagonist’s temperature is being taken, taking around seven minutes.</p><p>A:- ’Seven minutes! But they must be up!’</p><blockquote><p>B:- ‘Yes, but when you watch it, the time, it goes very slowly. I quite like the measuring, four times a day; for then you know what a minute - or seven of them- actually amounts to, up here in this place, where the seven days of the week whisk by the way they do!’</p><p>A:- ‘You say “actually”, but time isn’t actual. When it seems long to you, then it is long; when it seems short, why, then it is short. But how long or how short it actually is, that nobody knows.’</p><p>B: - ‘How so? - we do measure it. We have watches and calendars for this purpose; and when a month is up, why, then up it is, for you and for me, and for all of us.’</p><p>A:- ‘A minute is then as long as it seems to you when you measure yourself?’</p><p>B:- ‘A minute is as long- it lasts as long- as it takes the second hand of my watch to complete a circuit.’</p><p>A:- ‘But it takes a varied length of time for our senses. It is motion, isn’t it, motion in space? We measure time by space. How is that better than measuring space by time? Hamburg to Davos is twenty hours - that is, by train. On foot, how long is it? And in the mind, how long? Not a second. What is time? Space we perceive with our organs, senses of sight and touch.Good. But where is the organ of time? How can we measure something about which we know nothing. We say that ‘Time passes’. Sure, let it pass. But how does one measure that? We believe time flows evenly, with scientific precision, but does it? As far as our consciousness is considered, it does not - We only assume it does, for the sake of convenience; and our units of measurement are purely arbitrary, sheer conventions…’</p></blockquote></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:html -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>A much more nuanced take is taken up a few chapter later.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2>§4 <em>Excursus on the Sense of Time</em>;<em>pp:100</em></h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:html -->
<blockquote><p>There is after all , something peculiar about the process of habituating oneself in a new place, the often laborious fitting in and getting used to, which one undertakes for its own sake, and of set purpose to break it all off as soon as it is complete, or not long thereafter, and to return to one’s former state. </p><p>It is an interval, an interlude, inserted with the object of recreation, into the tenor of life’s main concerns; its purpose the relief of the organism, which is perpetually busy at its task of self-renewal, and which was in danger, almost in process, of being vitiated, slowed down, relaxed, by the bald, unjointed monotony of its daily course. </p><p>But what then is the cause of this relaxation, this slowing down that takes place when one does the same thing for too long at a time? It is not so much physical or mental fatigue or exhaustion, for if that were the case then complete rest would be the best restorative. It is rather something psychical; It means that the perception of time tends, through periods of unbroken uniformity, to fall away; the perception of time, so closely bound up with the consciousness of life that one may not be weakened without the other suffering a sensible impairment. </p><p>Many false conceptions are held concerning the nature of tedium. In general, it is thought that the interestingness and novelty of the time-content are what ‘make the time pass’; that is to say, shorten it; whereas monotony and emptiness check and restrain its flow. </p><p>This is only true with reservations. Vacuity, monotony, have, indeed the property of lingering out the moment and the hour and of making them tiresome. But they are capable of contracting and dissipating the larger, the very large time-units, to the point of reducing them to nothing at all. &gt; </p><p>And conversely, a full and interesting content can put wings to the hour and the day; yet it will lend to the general passage of time a weightiness, a breadth and solidity which cause the eventful years to flow far more slowly than those poor, bare, empty ones over which the wind passes and they are gone. Thus what we call tedium is rather an abnormal shortening of time consequent upon monotony.</p><p>Great spaces of time passed in unbroken uniformity tend to shrink together in a way to make the heart stop beating for fear; when one day is like all the others, then they are all like one; complete uniformity would make the longest life seem short, and as though it had stolen away from us unawares. </p><p>Habituation is a falling asleep or fatiguing of the sense of time; which explains why young years pass slowly, while later life flings itself faster and faster upon its course. We are aware that the intercalation of periods of change and novelty is the only means by which we can refresh our sense of time, strengthen, retard, rejuvenate it, and therewith renew our perception of life itself. </p><p>Such is the purpose of our changes of air and scene, of all our sojourns at cures and bathing resorts; it is the secret of the healing power of change and incident.</p><blockquote><p>Our first days in a new place; time has a youthful, that is to say, a broad and a sweeping, flow, persisting for some six to eight days. Then, as one ‘gets used to the place’, a gradual shrinkage makes itself felt. He who clings or, better expressed, wishes to cling to life, will shudder to see how the days grow light and lighter, how they scurry by like dead leaves, until the last week, of some four, perhaps, is uncannily fugitive and fleet. </p><p>On the other hand, the quickening of the sense of time will flow out beyond the interval and reassert itself after the return to ordinary existence: the first days at home after the holiday will be lived with broader flow, freshly and youthfully - but only the first few, for one adjusts oneself more quickly to the rule than to the exception; and if the sense of time be already weakened by age, or - and this is a low sign of vitality - it was never really well developed, one drowses quickly back into the old life, and after four-and-twenty hours it is as though one had never been away, and the journey had been but a watch in the night.</p></blockquote></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:html -->]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>174</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2020-05-30 15:47:27</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2020-05-30 15:47:27</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>experiencing-time-some-excerpts-from-thomas-manns-the-magic-mountain</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_publicize_job_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[44878887470]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>timeline_notification</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1590853650]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Evolution Creatice by Henri Bergson</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=177</link>
		<pubDate></pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=177</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>Evolution Creatice by Henri Bergson</h1>
<h2>Chapter 1: Evolving Life, Mechanism and Teleology</h2>
We are the ones with knowledge of our own existence. We are in various states in a multiplicity of composite sensations, feelings, ideas - We give some definiteness to such states, a block sequence sort of, <span class="math">\[s_{1},s_{2},s_{3}, \cdots s_{N}\]</span>
Within each state, no moment is the same, so that we have a sequence of moments for each state <span class="math">\[s_{11},s_{12},s_{13}, \cdots s_{1k}\forall s_{i}\]</span>

Say I am focusing on an external object for an extended period of time. Then, the only parameter of change is the time. Then in this continuity, it is us that impute discontinuity as an act of separation. A change that is catches our attention whilst focusing, and the awareness of the state itself induces a new state. Our memory is associated with these points of discontinuities off a continuous whole. Then off these discontinuous points, we again abstract a continuity through the ego consciousness.
<blockquote>Say we have a necklace of pearls with different colours. But in Reality they are a gradient where it becomes imperceptible as to when one colour ends and the next begins, so we demarcate boundaries and specify a colour for each section, that is, a pearl. The color then imputed is done so psychically. It is through the difference of colours we recognize the discreteness, otherwise if it were a single one, it would be no different from the gradient that is a continuous thread.</blockquote>
The above example is how Time is perceived. Since the present is a point which as soon realized becomes past, and we cannot catch the present, we make sense of time via <strong>duration</strong> aka <em>local memory</em>. Thus there are two ways of preserving the past, where one is like a hard-disk, of long term memories, the other is of duration, more like RAM, to make sense of the <strong>now</strong>. As it is obvious, we can't exactly relive a single moment since every moment is uniquely indexed.

Each moment thus contains the possibilities which branch out to the next node, an <em>instantaneous creation</em>. A puzzle is posed by Bergson as follows :-
<blockquote>Can an artist visualize a completed work before it has begun? And if he can, does that mean that work exists before existing?

Sometimes we don't obviously notice that each moment is unique(apart from time), but a block of solid object is undergoing changes at the molecular level.

A hydra has seven heads, then is it one hydra with seven heads or seven hydras with one body? Where in lies the identity? <span class="math">\[x = \frac{x}{7} .7\]</span></blockquote>
We are organisms, not mechanisms.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>177</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2020-05-30 15:49:47</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>draft</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Evolution Creatice by Henri Bergson</title>
		<link>https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=179</link>
		<pubDate></pubDate>
		<dc:creator>kabirchugh</dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://boundedlyirrational.wordpress.com/?p=179</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- wp:heading {"level":1} -->
<h1>Evolution Creatice by Henri Bergson</h1>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2>Chapter 1: Evolving Life, Mechanism and Teleology</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:preformatted -->
<pre class="wp-block-preformatted">We are the ones with knowledge of our own existence. We are in various states in a multiplicity of composite sensations, feelings, ideas - We give some definiteness to such states, a block sequence sort of, $$<span class="math">\s_{1},s_{2},s_{3}, \cdots s_{N}\]</span>$$

Within each state, no moment is the same, so that we have a sequence of moments for each state <span class="math">\[s_{11},s_{12},s_{13}, \cdots s_{1k}\forall s_{i}\]</span></pre>
<!-- /wp:preformatted -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Say I am focusing on an external object for an extended period of time. Then, the only parameter of change is the time. Then in this continuity, it is us that impute discontinuity as an act of separation. A change that is catches our attention whilst focusing, and the awareness of the state itself induces a new state. Our memory is associated with these points of discontinuities off a continuous whole. Then off these discontinuous points, we again abstract a continuity through the ego consciousness.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Say we have a necklace of pearls with different colours. But in Reality they are a gradient where it becomes imperceptible as to when one colour ends and the next begins, so we demarcate boundaries and specify a colour for each section, that is, a pearl. The color then imputed is done so psychically. It is through the difference of colours we recognize the discreteness, otherwise if it were a single one, it would be no different from the gradient that is a continuous thread.</p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The above example is how Time is perceived. Since the present is a point which as soon realized becomes past, and we cannot catch the present, we make sense of time via <strong>duration</strong> aka <em>local memory</em>. Thus there are two ways of preserving the past, where one is like a hard-disk, of long term memories, the other is of duration, more like RAM, to make sense of the <strong>now</strong>. As it is obvious, we can't exactly relive a single moment since every moment is uniquely indexed. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Each moment thus contains the possibilities which branch out to the next node, an <em>instantaneous creation</em>. A puzzle is posed by Bergson as follows :-</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:quote -->
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Can an artist visualize a completed work before it has begun? And if he can, does that mean that work exists before existing?</p><p>Sometimes we don't obviously notice that each moment is unique(apart from time), but a block of solid object is undergoing changes at the molecular level.</p><p>A hydra has seven heads, then is it one hydra with seven heads or seven hydras with one body? Where in lies the identity? $$<span class="math">\[x = \frac{x}{7} .7\]$$</span></p></blockquote>
<!-- /wp:quote -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>We are organisms, not mechanisms. </p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>179</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2020-05-30 15:51:47</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>0000-00-00 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>draft</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
